<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-05T20:41:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working Agreements, A Must Have For Agile Teams]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/11/05/working-agreements/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-05T19:57:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/11/05/working-agreements</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this you probably have good understanding of agile teams characteristics.
So you know that agile teams are not just a group of individuals working each one alone, on their individual goals or within their area of expertise.   <br/>
And that Agile team members share common goals, work together, and support each other in achieving their commitments, in a all the team succeed or all the team fail spirit. <br/>
Finally, Agile teams are self-organized and their day to day activity involve increased communication and collaboration.</p>

<p>But you might be wondering what make agile teams reach top performance and effectiveness. Interested to know ?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-11-05-working-agreements/f4-1.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In 1965, Bruce Tuckman was the first to propose a team development model. <br/>
In his model, a team need to go through four stages in order to reach effectiveness and performance.
At the start, the team is formed, members agree on the goals and challenges, they tend to behave individually, this the first stage, called forming.<br/>
A bit later, conflicts will arise as each individual start establishing his position in the group, this is the second stage, it&rsquo;s called storming. <br/>
In the third stage, called norming, clarity for each individual role and consensus are established. The team&rsquo;s performance and effectiveness improve.<br/>
When group norms and roles are established, group members are autonomous and are able to handle the decision-making process without supervision, focusing on achieving common goals, the team reach top performance and effectiveness. It&rsquo;ll be then in the fourth stage, called performing. <br/>
Agile or not, this model applies to any team, and an agile team can accelerate its progress toward performing by
making use of the &ldquo;Working Agreement&rdquo; tool.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-11-05-working-agreements/tuckman.jpg"></p>

<p>So what are &ldquo;Working Agreements&rdquo; ?
<strong>Working agreement</strong> are a set of rules or protocols the team agree to follow when working together.
They help the team meet its goals, establishing a one team culture and developing a sense of shared responsibility.<br/>
They also help team members to increase the awareness of their own behavior and empower each one of them to act.</p>

<p><strong>Working agreements</strong> are owned and set by the team.
All team members have the responsibility to question anyone not following the rules.<br/>
This removes the perception of personal attacks and confrontation.<br/>
Working agreements need to be continuously improved, this can be done by the team regularly asking the question &ldquo;Should we update them?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Good working agreements are focused on amplifying desired patterns of behavior.
They are aimed at helping the team members achieve their tasks and team-work goals.
They can be generalizable and are written with minimum specifications.</p>

<p>Three key elements make working agreements effective in helping the team.
The first one is their importance to the team : working agreements need to be fully supported by each team member, and members are reminded when agreements are not followed.  
The second one is their number: the set of Working agreements need to have a limited number of rules. The team has to review regularly the list to ensure it contains the rules the team needs to focus on.      
The third one is documented: by documented I mean defined and known by all team members. Ideally the should be made visible by posting them on a wall or an electronic board.    
Following these three rules will help you ensure effective working agreements fro your team.  </p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-11-05-working-agreements/f4-2.png"></p>

<p>A team can setup its first working agreement during a retrospective or a dedicated session.<br/>
The session can be facilitated by the product owner, the scrum master or any other team member.  <br/>
The facilitator start by explaining the why and what of working agreements. <br/>
He then give some examples like: be on time, respect estimates, how to address bugs/fires during Sprint, etc.<br/>
He then ask the team to suggest points that are crucial for their improvement and the reasons why they think those should be work agreements. <br/>
The team then take a vote to pick the top five/seven ideas as a work agreements.
The work doesn&rsquo;t stop here, as I said before, the list should be reviewed regularly, retrospective meeting is an option.<br/>
Once team members feel they are doing well on one agreement, they can replace it with another agreement to focus on. It&rsquo;s a good idea to keep the removed items in a sort of culture book for newcomers, after all the item was removed because it became a habit for the team members and anyone joining the team need to learn about it.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em><br/>
<a href="http://www.moviestillsdb.com/movies/fantastic-four-i1502712" title="Fantastic Four">Fantastic Four | moviestillsdb | Copyright by respective production studio and/or distributor. Intended for editorial use only.</a>, <a href="http://stephengraves.us/category/leadership/" title="Tips on Improving Team Performance">Tips on Improving Team Performance | stephengraves.us (2013).</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 Things That Can Ruin Your Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/07/28/6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-28T20:14:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/07/28/6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuous improvement is one of the necessary pillars when it comes to Agile.<br/>
Failing to improve your process won&rsquo;t let you unlock its full potential nor reach the benefits promised by Agile.  <br/>
But whether you&rsquo;re practicing agile or not, I&rsquo;m bet that you do care about improving what your doing.  <br/>
Identifying things to improve can be done by conducting a retrospective session.<br/>
Retrospective is a special meeting that takes place at the end of an iteration or a project.<br/>
It is a dedicated moment where the team take time to inspect the work done and try to spot opportunities for improvement.<br/>
Planning and conducting retrospectives is not hard, but some pitfalls might prevent you from getting out the desired outcome. Read on to know what are the 6 things that could ruin your retrospectives.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Totally winging it</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/totally-winging-it.jpg">
As any other work session or meeting a retrospective should be structured and activities prepared.<br/>
A retrospective is usually composed from several activities that will help the team spot imrovement opportunities and deduce relevant actions.  <br/>
To achieve this goal the activities need to fit well together, the timing already figured out and sometime materials need to be prepared up-front, like posters, cards, etc.<br/>
Improvising your session will most probably lead to poor outcomes. <br/>
My advise: take the time, 15 to 20 minutes are enough to structure a retrospective.<br/>
Choose a theme and the sequence of the activities, take some time to refresh your memory on how they are conducted, specify the time you&rsquo;re going to allocate to each one. Share the agenda with the team at the start.</p>

<h1>Fighting Hunger</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/fighting-hunger.jpg">
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needs#Physiological_needs">Maslow&rsquo;s hierarchy of needs</a> tells us that food is one of the very basic human needs. <br/>
You need to remeber that whenever you find yourself in the obligation to plan a retrospective during lunchtime.<br/>
It&rsquo;s better to avoid such situation, participants will be only thinking on when the session will end so that they can get to eat. At worst if you can&rsquo;t avoid it, do order food for the team, competing against hunger is a lost battle. <br/>
As a general rule, it&rsquo;s a good idea to have some fruits or candies available for participants. This will help them to remain energized and contributes to the good working atmosphere. <br/>
Don&rsquo;t forget to schedule a short break in the middle of the session, let people get out of the room, fulfill their needs, grab a cup of cofee or a bottle of water.</p>

<h1>Lightning Speed Retrospective</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/lightning-speed-retrospective.jpg">
A typical retrospective will take between 1h30min and 2h to deliver good actionable items. It&rsquo;s simply the time needed to collect the data, analyze it and deduce improvement actions.<br/>
If the team is lacking time, the last thing to is to shorten the retrospective. Doing that will only lead to the opposite desired outcome, wasting time on an inefficient session. <br/>
When the team find itself unable to allocate the appropriate time to its retrospective, my advice is to exceptionally skip the occurrence, secure the next retrospective and make sure the team identify what need to be done to avoid hitting the same issue in the future.</p>

<h1>Skipping the Starter</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/skipping-the-starter.jpg">
It&rsquo;s a good practice to start any work session with an ice breaker. Why ? Studies have shown that when a  participant in a meeting doesn&rsquo;t speak during the first five minutes, he usually remain silent till the end of the session. <br/>
You don&rsquo;t want that to happen to your retrospective, on the contrary you want all the participants to speak up and share their concerns and ideas on improvement. <br/>
By skipping your check-in activity you are giving each participant the permission to remain silent for the rest of the session.
Spending 5 or 10 minutes in an ice break at the start of the retrospective is good investment to make that can only improve the outcomes.</p>

<h1>Skipping the Desert</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/skipping-the-desert.jpg">
Retrospecting is part of your process, so as the rest it can and need to be improved constantly.<br/>
The check-out activity is your opportunity to get feedback from the participants in order to improve the next occurrences.<br/>
Don&rsquo;t skip it, make sure you plan a &ldquo;Return on Time Invested&rdquo; or a &ldquo;Plus/Delta&rdquo; activity to get insights on what can be improved.</p>

<h1>All Talk and No Action</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/all-talk-and-no-action.jpg">
Your team is extremely busy and improvement actions are piling up in a todo list somewhere.<br/>
Clearly the teams not improving, and it will soon start loosing faith in retrospectives and see them rather as waste.<br/>
This pitfall can be avoided by simply adding the identified improvement actions to the team backlog and treat them as any other task in the backlog.  Apply to them the same prioritizing technique and plan them accordingly. <br/>
In the Scrum framework this technique is called &ldquo;Scrumming the Scrum&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Simple Way to Run a Solution Focused Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/06/18/a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-18T08:03:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/06/18/a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While attending to a <a href="https://management30.com/events/two-day-course/">2-day course on Management 3.0</a>, on of the new things I discovered was the &ldquo;solution focus&rdquo; approach to improving things. Googling on the matter I learned that this technique come from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solution_focused_brief_therapy">&ldquo;Solution focused brief therapy&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/problem-solution.jpg"></p>

<p>In a solution focused brief therapy (SFBT) the patient is asked to focus on solution-building rather than problem-solving. This can be achieved by exploring current resources and future hopes rather than present problems and past causes. <br/>
First thing that popped to my mind when discovering SFBT, is its similarity to an agile retrospective.<br/>
Retrospective main aim is to spot improvement opportunities and come up with actions to make things better in the future.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been conducting and participating to retrospectives for several years now, but unlike SFBT, we were often digging to identify the root-cause of problems and then trying to figure out solutions.<br/>
SFBT opened a new perspective for me. Finding the root-cause in a retrospective is putting the effort in looking into the past. Applying SFBT to a retrospective implied not putting the effort on analyzing what happened but rather putting it in finding an action that can lead to a better future.</p>

<p>How can you do that? Here&rsquo;s the simple recipe I used.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When conducting retrospective I like to follow the structure proposed in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w8w-dFrmovQ">&ldquo;Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great&rdquo;</a> by Esther Derby and Diana Larsen. I always structure my retrospective accordingly.</p>

<p>I start by a <strong><em>set the stage</em></strong> activity to break the ice, and a <strong><em>closing</em></strong> activity to share appreciations or get feedback. You can compare these to a starter and a desert in 3-courses menu.<br/>
The main course is where most of the work happen, and it goes like this.<br/>
It starts with an activity to <strong><em>gather data</em></strong> regarding the last iteration from the participants followed by an activity enabling <strong><em>insights generation</em></strong> leading the team to <strong><em>deciding what to do</em></strong>.</p>

<p>The <strong><em>generate insight</em></strong> activity is usually where the team look at the problem, brainstorm to identify the root. Classical activities that can be used are 5-whys analysis, fishbone, etc. It&rsquo;s then followed by an activity to identify the actions and <strong><em>decide what to do</em></strong> like SMART goals, Short subjects, etc.</p>

<p>In a <strong>solution focused</strong> retrospective both activities can be replaced by a single solution oriented activity conducted as follow:</p>

<p>Assuming that the team did a <strong><em>gather data</em></strong> activity and identified themes to work on, divide the participants in groups of 3 or 4, each group takes a theme to work on. In some cases it might possible for the group to work on all the themes.</p>

<p>Ask the group to consider the following two questions:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Regarding the chosen theme, on a scale from 1 to 10 where do you think we are today?</strong></li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/rating-scale.png"></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>What action cans be done in the next iteration accomplish a +1 improvement?</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Then ask the group to work 4 small iterations, each one of 6 minutes as follows:</p>

<p>Iteration 1 - <strong>On your own, self brain dumping / Silence / Post&#8217;it.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 2 - <strong>Together, Share.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 3 - <strong>Aggregate &amp; Consolidate.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 4 - <strong>Finalize &amp; prepare a 1&#8217;30 pitch to share with the other groups.</strong></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/post-it.jpg"></p>

<p>I usually remind the groups to make us of the SMART goals approach when deciding on the actions for the next iteration.</p>

<p>This recipe worked well for me, I found a good way to make the team discover new ways of identifying improvements actions. It&rsquo;s also a good way to bring novelty to the retrospective and avoid falling into monotony.  I&rsquo;m I&rsquo;ll be making use form time to time of it in my future working sessions. If you like this activity or would like to propose changes, please do not hesitate to leave your highly welcome comment.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thesaleswhisperer/14188549988/" title="problems solutions entrepreneurship">problems solutions entrepreneurship</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jogibaer2/5459043426/" title="Post-It">Post-It</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Software Development Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/04/30/building-a-software-development-team/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-30T22:06:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/04/30/building-a-software-development-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying to build an effective software development team ?
Here are some key elements that might help you.
<a href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-04-30-building-a-software-development-team/Building_a_Software_Development_Team.png"><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-04-30-building-a-software-development-team/Building_a_Software_Development_Team.png"></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Building a Software Development Team</p>

<blockquote><p>SCRUM</p>

<blockquote><p>Provide a SCRUM training for the team</p>

<p>Convince all team members take the lead in a round robin fashion on the scrum ceremonies facilitation (Sprint Review &amp; Planning, Retrospectives &hellip;)</p>

<p>Define the DoR : Definition of Ready</p>

<blockquote><p>Clear Acceptance test<br/>
Shared minimal design</p></blockquote>

<p>Define the DoD : Definition of Done</p>

<blockquote><p>Build pipeline is green<br/>
Minimal documentation</p></blockquote>

<p>Regular Backlog Grooming<br/>
Poker Estimation</p>

<blockquote><p>Story point as time unit is not allowed</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Ops</p>

<blockquote><p>Configure a continuous integration pipline</p>

<blockquote><p>Build (includes unit tests)<br/>
Code Inspection<br/>
Integration Tests<br/>
Performance Tests<br/>
Automate Tests</p></blockquote>

<p>Define Quality Gates</p>

<p>Build Pipline Monitor</p></blockquote>

<p>Code</p>

<blockquote><p>TDD / Test First</p>

<p>Clean Code</p>

<blockquote><p>Simple Design</p>

<blockquote><p>First make it work, then make it simple, only then make it fast<br/>
KISS<br/>
YAGNI<br/>
SOLID<br/>
Modular</p></blockquote>

<p>Understandable code</p>

<blockquote><p>Clear Naming<br/>
Comment Unclear Parts of Code<br/>
Self-documenting Code<br/>
Cohesive Methods and Classes</p></blockquote>

<p>Follow the Boy Scout Rule Leave your code better than you found it</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Team Work</p>

<blockquote><p>Define Work Agreements</p>

<p>Collective Code Ownership</p>

<blockquote><p>Define Team Coding Conventions</p></blockquote>

<p>Continuous Improvement Culture</p>

<blockquote><p>Improvement and exploration tasks are part of the sprint backlog</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Don't Like The @author Tags]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/03/03/why-i-dont-like-the-at-author-tags/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-03T23:59:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/03/03/why-i-dont-like-the-at-author-tags</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javadoc">JavaDoc</a> has a <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/documentation/index-137868.html#@author">@author</a> tag that can be used to assign a programmer at the overview, package and class level.<br/>
As a software engineer working in a team I never liked this tag.<br/>
As I became a development manager, my unlikeness increased even more.<br/>
This feeling is fed by negative impacts on both the &ldquo;<a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/collective.html">Collective Ownership</a>&rdquo; and the &ldquo;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor">Bus factor</a>&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-03-03-why-i-dont-like-the-at-author-tags/share.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p><a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/collective.html">Collective Ownership</a> is an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extreme_programming">Extreme Programming</a> rule that encourages everyone to contribute to all parts of the code.<br/>
Any developer can change any line of code to add functionality, fix bugs, improve designs or refactor.<br/>
Collective Ownership mentality is great because every developer feels like he own the code.<br/>
This drives quality up and fuels the passion that leads to inspiration.<br/>
I&rsquo;m a strong believer in the benefits of this approach and always encouraging my development teams to adopt it.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor">Bus factor</a> is the answer to a simple question: &ldquo;how many people would need to get hit by a bus before this code collapses due to lack of knowledgeable or competent personnel?&rdquo; <br/>
You want that number to be high.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/documentation/index-137868.html#@author">@author</a> tag is a signpost telling everyone else to stay away:
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m the owner, this file belongs to me, no one else should touch it or at best you need to ask for my permission before modifying the code&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-03-03-why-i-dont-like-the-at-author-tags/do-not-touch.jpg"></p>

<p>It creates an single developer ownership mentality of portions of the code driving the bus factor toward one, and thus putting the project at risk.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using the <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/documentation/index-137868.html#@author">@author</a> tag, I hope I convinced you to stop or at least made you aware of its danger.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/opensourceway/5752191166/" title="Improving the speed and quality of research via shared algorithm implementations">Improving the speed and quality of research via shared algorithm implementations</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>,
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/luccawithcheese/3467529252/" title="You Don't touch the MOMA">You Don&rsquo;t touch the MOMA</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is It Realistic To Manage Closely Several Agile Teams]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/01/26/is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-26T00:20:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/01/26/is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been recently promoted to manage a division in software development department of my company.<br/>
Till then I was used to managing one team at a once, not exceeding 10 people in size.<br/>
Now I find myself with 8 teams to manage having each a size ranging from 4 to 7 people.</p>

<p>In my previous role I was comfortable with adopting the SCRUM agile framework and quite used to play the role of the scrum master and to participate actively to the product owner role. <br/>
Some of the new teams were already trying to follow the agile practices, some were still working with rather a traditional waterfall approach.
So naturally I found myself driving the teams to adopt the SCRUM framework.
I made sure to share with them my return on experience and to point out the pitfalls and the small details that can make a difference.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/scrum.png"></p>

<p>Fortunately for me the resistance to change was less than expected. <br/>
All the teams were eager to try the new framework and to improve their agile practices.    <br/>
This is when things start to get a bit more complicated.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>Among the teams that had tried agile methods, some had tried the SCRUM framework before but ended up by letting it go. Some accommodated the framework with what they thought it would suit them better and thus were practicing a modified custom version.</p>

<p>This reminded me of the caveat entitled <a href="https://books.google.fr/books?id=pjLcBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT21&amp;lpg=PT21&amp;dq=%22Do+not+change+scrum%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ZLjZe7HpGC&amp;sig=fZakjNenlohycnYqsULErZxMPlY&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiVm-C3gMbKAhXLthoKHcC1AKgQ6AEIHzAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"><strong><em>Do not change scrum</em></strong> <em>in The Enterprise and Scrum (by Ken Schwaber)</em></a></p>

<p>Having observed that, it was clear to me that I had to bring the teams to the required level of understanding of the methodology and to help them in the adoption and ramp up phase.</p>

<p>Doing that was not a problem for me, on the contrary I enjoy playing the role of the scrum master in an agile development team. The problem was rather a capacity one, will I have enough time to do it right.</p>

<p>You might say, sure it won’t take that long to train a group of people to an agile methodology. <br/>
I can’t disagree with that, after all I had my scrum master certification after a two days training.<br/>
But what I also know, is that it took me nearly two years of practice to be able to take full advantage of the framework. So when I say doing it right, I mean working closely with each team trying to share with them what I learnt and helping them reaching the tipping point to becoming agile.</p>

<p>The couple of teams I had selected to start with showed high appreciation of the help they received and I could instantly see the difference and the positive impact on their day to day job.</p>

<p>But till now I haven’t managed to keep a regular pace to assist closely all the teams in this adoption process and this doesn’t make me feel satisfied. With all the responsibilities I have to assume I never get the time needed to accompany the teams in all of their agile ceremonies.<br/>
Since a couple of days I’ve been asking myself, assuming I had nothing else to do, is it possible to do such a close follow up? That’s when I decide to do the math.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/calculator.jpg"></p>

<p>For one team, per iteration of two weeks, I will need to allocate:    <br/>
- 3 hours for the demo/sprint planning   <br/>
- 2 hours to retrospect<br/>
- 2 hours to participate to the backlog grooming  <br/>
- 10 x 15 minutes of daily stand up</p>

<p>This leads us to 9 hours and 30 minutes per team every two weeks, multiplying this by 8 leads us to a total of 76 hours. So at the end doing the close follow up with all teams will require me to allocate 38 hours per week for this activity alone; a full time job!</p>

<p>Although this seem to fit in my working hours habit I doubt I will go that way.<br/>
Why? Because the expectations from my new role go beyond that, I have other duties to fulfill that are part of the role and that are time consuming too, nearly half of my time.</p>

<p>So what next? Well no doubt, I’ll need to make a choice, follow the most important things and delegate the rest.<br/>
First action is to ask a team member to play the role of the scrum master for a given iteration. All team members will play this role in a round robin fashion. <br/>
Second action is to skip attending the daily standups, this will let me gain back 10 hours per week, and I believe the teams will be able to conduct them efficiently on their own with the help of the assigned scrum master.</p>

<p>Next step will be to opt out from the retrospectives once the team is used to conducting them. Of course I will provide my notes to a team member and ask him to represent me. This will let me on the long term get back 8 hours.</p>

<p>So in total I will need to allocate 20 hours per week to perform the remaining activities which seem reasonable. I believe this close follow up will yield to a better results, I’ll be trying this and learning from the experience.</p>

<p>Interested in the outcome? Stay tuned.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/scrum-glasses.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ansik/304526237/" title="calculator">calculator</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/neighborhoodnini/9650231200/" title="Perpetual Scrum Google Glasses">Perpetual Scrum Google Glasses</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/cadsonline/470108485/" title="scrum diagram">scrum diagram</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beating The Meeting Run]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T20:00:46+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just one full week in my new job, that&rsquo;s what it took me  to experience a new kind of sport, the &ldquo;Meeting Run&rdquo;.<br/>
And as a good friend of mine would say, like everything there are always two sides. <br/>
In what I experienced I encountered a good one and a bad one (and no there&rsquo;s no <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0060196/">ugly</a> one, at least not yet).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/time.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>
The good side was that my <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.fitness&amp;hl=fr">Google Fit application</a> started congratulating me everyday for meeting my 1 hour walking goal, and sometimes I would even hit that by noon!</p>

<p>In 15 years in software development, it never happened to me during work days ! (yes I know you might argue that smartphones and activity tracking applications are rather recent, so you&rsquo;ll have to take my word for that).   <br/>
This is great news, I finally managed to exercise and work at the same time, there&rsquo;s a hope for me to loose the kilos I gained this summer!</p>

<p>And as you might suspect there&rsquo;s no free lunch so where&rsquo;s the catch? <br/>
Well here&rsquo;s the bad side ; since all meetings were adjacent, it was just impossible for me to arrive at time to any meeting.<br/>
And it really annoyed me, I always used to do my best to be at most on time if not a couple of minutes before. <br/>
But I admit when I was able to do this my calendar looked a little bit different than it is now.<br/>
The same pattern occurred the whole week, and I started getting calls from people waiting for me in the next meeting.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, this is the end, I said to myself sadly ; bye bye punctuality and welcome reality &hellip;<br/>
Fortunately a little voice in my head was whispering &ldquo;no, no, no&rdquo; and when I paid attention I heard it say &ldquo;&hellip; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory">broken window theory</a> &hellip; <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Professionalism/Diane_Vaughan_and_the_normalization_of_deviance">normalization of deviance</a> &hellip;&rdquo;. <br/>
And it just hit me, it was clear to me that I was slipping into these anti-patterns.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/broken-window.png"></p>

<p>Accepting being late to meeting is a clear illustration of &ldquo;Diane Vaughan&rsquo;s normalization of deviance&rdquo;.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Social normalization of deviance means that people within the organization become so much accustomed to a deviant behavior that they don&rsquo;t consider it as deviant, <br/>
despite the fact that they far exceed their own rules for the elementary safety&rdquo;. People grow more accustom to the deviant behavior the more it occurs. To people outside of the organization, <br/>
the activities seem deviant; however, people within the organization do not recognize the deviance because it is seem as a normal occurrence. <br/>
In hindsight, people within the organization realize that their seemingly normal behavior was deviant.</p></blockquote>

<p>And worse, it&rsquo;s the first broken window I&rsquo;m inviting to my work habits. What next, I&rsquo;ll start accepting code with less quality, shipping untested code to production, and end up considering compiler warnings as just normal messages! <br/>
NO, NO, NO, this is not an option. <br/>
But how to avoid that?  How to avoid adjacent meetings? One might be tempted by defining a process to manage his calendar.  <br/>
And start thinking about rules, like meetings should not be adjacent, or they should never be scheduled to start at hh:00 but rather hh:05.<br/>
But how to enforce that, you might think about developing an outlook extension for that &hellip; <br/>
That was really compelling for the software engineer in me, but for the pragmatic developer it looked complex and too much, it also required everybody to be aligned with the rules when booking meetings.  <br/>
I needed something that I can achieve on my own, where I have full control to apply it, something that would be simple.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/punctuality.png"></p>

<p>Suddenly it all became clear. The solution is simple, do like the <a href="https://www.bitcoinmining.com/">Bitcoin miner</a>. A Bitcoin miner will keep a small fee for himself when validating a transaction.<br/>
All I have to do is the same, I&rsquo;ll just apply a tax to the meeting time and take 5 minutes for me.<br/>
This will let me leave the meeting 5 minutes early, of course I&rsquo;ll inform people at the start that I&rsquo;ll be leaving early.<br/>
And that&rsquo;s it ! A simple and actionable solution.  <br/>
Abiding by this rule I will hopefully get back punctuality and avoid annoying people by arriving late to meetings.</p>

<p><strong>So from now on, if you&rsquo;re in a meeting with me, be advised, there&rsquo;s a fee, I&rsquo;ll be leaving 5 minutes early!  </strong></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/4961717384/" title="time">time</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/26008085@N07/2739411797/" title="Broken Windows Theory In Action">Broken Windows Theory In Action</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/artistick-nik/5616580252/" title="punctuality">punctuality</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Driving Technical Change Cheat Sheet]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/26/driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-26T11:01:58+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/26/driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I enjoyed reading the book <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/trevan/driving-technical-change">Driving Technical Change: <em>Why People on Your Team Don’t Act on Good Ideas, and How to Convince Them They Should</em></a> by Adobe software evangelist <a href="http://www.terrenceryan.com/">Terrence Ryan</a>.<br/>
It made me recall of a lot of situations I encounter in my daily job. I also discovered new approaches that could come in handy in the future.<br/>
I recommend it to any person having a role to play in a software development division.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-26-driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/cheat-sheet.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my takeaways cheat sheet.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Skeptic Patterns</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-26-driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/Skeptic-Patterns.png"></p>

<h2>Techniques</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-26-driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/Techniques.png"></p>

<h2>Strategy</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-26-driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/Strategy.png"></p>

<h2>Skeptic/Technique Matrix</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-26-driving-technical-change-cheat-sheet/skeptic-technique-matrix.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile Retrospectives Using Trello]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-20T20:31:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a distributed agile team working from Paris and Beirut, remote retrospectives are part of our rituals.<br/>
To conduct these remote retrospectives, we have settled on using <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a>. <br/>
My colleague <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/">BOURGAU Philippe</a> has <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">blogged on what we tried</a> and how we ended up by opting for Trello.<br/>
Since then we have made some improvements on speeding up the meeting preparation, and I think it&rsquo;s time to share them.
<img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/trello.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As you might know, retrospectives activities are recurrent, it&rsquo;s not unlikely to redo the same activity a couple of retrospectives later.<br/>
So it was natural for us to start creating boards to be used as templates for the activities. <br/>
These boards served as a starting point when setting up a session and were improved continuously. <br/>
So how is this used practically ?<br/>
<img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/gald-sad-mad.png">
In our case, a facilitator is responsible of preparing and animating each session. <br/>
When preparing the session, instead of creating each activity board from scratch, the facilitator had now a catalog in which he could choose the activities. <br/>
All he had to do is to copy the board, give him a specific name and share it with the team. <br/>
Each board contains a short description of the activity, and a suitable setup to conduct it.<br/>
In reality the facilitator still created boards from scratch, but only when no template was available.<br/>
But now, instead of doing it only for his session, he took the time to first create a template and then copy it into his session. <br/>
This way he would have contributed to the enrichment of the catalog and facilitated the preparation of upcoming sessions. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve been doing this for quite some time and I think it&rsquo;s worth to share it with the agile community. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve learned a lot form others&#8217; experiments and it&rsquo;s time for us to contribute back with what we experimented.  <br/>
I&rsquo;ve started publishing some of the templates I made to the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">Agile Retrospectives</a> space, it&rsquo;s a public Trello team.
As I&rsquo;m writing this post, there are six published templates. I&rsquo;ll soon be asking other contributors on the team to share their work too, so stay tuned for more templates. <br/>
I hope you will find this useful for your retrospectives, and if you do use a template and have any improvement to make, don&rsquo;t hesitate to join the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">team</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Your XOOM 2 Kid Safe]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/11/making-your-xoom-2-kid-safe/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-11T21:08:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/11/making-your-xoom-2-kid-safe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of years ago I bought the Motorola Xoom 2 for my personal usage.<br/>
It was my first Android tablet and I mainly planned to use it to make Skype calls, browse the Internet and read some e-books.
We also used it to play nursery rhyme videos to our last-born.   <br/>
As he grew, he was convinced that it was &ldquo;his&rdquo; tablet and started to play games on it.<br/>
It didn&rsquo;t take him long to figure out how to look for YouTube videos or to install new games, this is when troubles started.
     <img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-11-making-your-xoom-2-kid-safe/Xoom2.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It was clear for us that, unless we wanted to constantly supervise him while using the tablet, we needed a strict parental control.<br/>
The parental control is not built-in in the Xoom 2, but a lot of options are available in Google Play.<br/>
Options varies from locking apps, to safe browsers, and screen time management apps.</p>

<p>After trying some different strategies this is what I found most suitable.</p>

<p>I first rooted the tablet in order to install an ad blocker. I chose to do this because most of the free games have pop-up ads.<br/>
Beside being annoying, they are difficult for kids to skip. Most of the time the lead my kid to some content that I do not approve.</p>

<p>Then I installed <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kiddoware.kidsplace">Kids Place - Parental Control</a> from <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/developer?id=kiddoware">kiddoware</a>.  <br/>
Beside restricting the kids to apps you have approved, Kids Place can be configured to override the &lsquo;home&rsquo; button and to run on tablet boot.<br/>
Additional plugins such as a safe video player, safe browser and screen time management can be installed too.
    <img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-11-making-your-xoom-2-kid-safe/Xoom2-Kids-Place.png">
With this configuration the Xoom 2 became a child safe Android tablet that I was confident to leave in my kid&rsquo;s hands.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in rooting your Xoom 2, here&rsquo;s the steps to follow:<br/>
1. On tablet go to Settings -> Developers Options and enable the Usb Debugging option.      <br/>
2. On tablet go to Settings -> Security and enable Unknown Sources option. <br/>
2. Plug your tablet to your PC, check the device manager to make sure the driver is properly installed.<br/>
If you see a yellow exclamation mark next to the Xoom 2 driver, right-click on it, go to &lsquo;Driver&rsquo; tab, click &lsquo;Update Driver&rsquo;, click &lsquo;Browse my computer &hellip;&rsquo;, click the &lsquo;Let me pick &hellip;&rsquo;<br/>
From the list choose the &lsquo;Android ADB Composite Driver&rsquo;<br/>
    <img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-09-11-making-your-xoom-2-kid-safe/adb-driver.png">  <br/>
3. Download and unzip <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/android-utils/blob/master/Xoom2-IceCreamSandwich-RootFiles.zip?raw=true">Xoom2-IceCreamSandwich-RootFiles</a><br/>
4. Run DroidRazrRoot404.bat<br/>
5. Your tablet will reboot and you will have gained root access.</p>

<p>To block ads do the following:<br/>
1. download and install <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/android-utils/blob/master/AdAway-release_Build-Oct.13.2014.apk?raw=true">AdAway</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/android-utils/blob/master/adblockplusandroid-1.3.apk?raw=true">AdBlockPlus</a><br/>
2. Grant both apps root privileges when it&rsquo;s asked for.</p>

<p>Now you&rsquo;re ready to install <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kiddoware.kidsplace">Kids Place - Parental Control</a> and make your tablet safer for kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unlock Full Android Power To Your Amazon Fire HD 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/23/unlock-full-android-power-to-your-amazon-fire-hd-6/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-23T21:33:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/23/unlock-full-android-power-to-your-amazon-fire-hd-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently acquired an <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00KC6I06S/ref=ods_fs_far">Amazon Fire HD 6</a> tablet.<br/>
I had high hopes that it would be the perfect tablet to read books, use <a href="www.skype.com">Skype</a> and check mails.<br/>
I found its price attractive with respect to its characteristics, and being an old customer of Amazon I was confident that the tablet will meet my expectations.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-23-unlock-full-android-power-to-your-amazon-fire-hd-6/fire-gapps.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It was no surprise to me to find out that the Fire HD 6 had only access to the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kindle-Store/b?ie=UTF8&amp;node=133140011">Kindle Store</a>. My unpleasant surprise was discovering that <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/dev?id=5700313618786177705&amp;hl=fr">Google applications</a> are not available in the Amazon store.</p>

<p>Using the Fire HD 6 without the Gmail, Hangout, Drive and other google applications was not an option for me.<br/>
Knowing that the Fire HD 6 is running Android, I started looking for a way to install the Google Apps.</p>

<p>There are a lot of information on how to root the Fire HD 6 and install Google applications, unfortunately all resources are not up to date or detailed enough. It took me some time to figure it out, and after two attempts, I managed to get everything working perfectly. Here are the detailed steps that helped me get there.</p>

<p>To install Google application you need root access to the tablet.<br/>
In order to get root access the Fire HD 6 must be running the Fire OS 4.5.3 or below.  <br/>
If you, being an enthusiast like me, have upgraded you tablet OS as soon as you received it you will have to apply the following steps to downgrade back to Fire OS 4.5.3. If you&rsquo;re already running 4.5.3 skip to step 4.</p>

<ol>
<li>Install the Fire OS 5.0 developer preview

<ul>
<li>Go to <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/public/solutions/platforms/android-fireos?sc_channel=EM&amp;sc_campaign=FireOSPreview&amp;sc_%20detail=GetPreview">Fire OS Developer Preview</a></li>
<li>Press the yellow <code>developer preview</code> button on the right side of the page</li>
<li>Log into your amazon account</li>
<li>Choose your device</li>
<li>Go to system settings/device options/system updates and press the check for updates button</li>
<li>Follow the instruction and complete the update</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://developer.amazon.com/public/community/post/Tx3RZFBU0KJTSWS/Setting-up-the-ADB-Driver-for-Kindle-Fire-Devices">Set up ADB on your computer and enable ADB on your tablet</a>

<ul>
<li>Installtion of the ADB driver on my windows 8.1 didn&rsquo;t work well. The trick that worked for me was to delete the Fire device from the device manger and to manually add an android ADB composite driver.
<img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-23-unlock-full-android-power-to-your-amazon-fire-hd-6/android-adb.png"></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Install Fire OS 4.5.3:

<ul>
<li>Download the <a href="https://kindle-fire-updates.s3.amazonaws.com/update-kindle-20.4.5.3_user_453011120.bin">4.5.3 firmware</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/fire-hd6-android">apk files</a></li>
<li>Connect the tablet to computer and run the command <code>adb reboot recovery</code></li>
<li>Use volume keys and power button to navigate to <code>Apply update from ADB</code></li>
<li>From the computer type <code>adb sideload update-kindle-20.4.5.3_user_453011120.bin</code></li>
<li>From tablet select <code>wipe data/factory reset</code></li>
<li>From tablet select <code>reboot system</code></li>
<li>Complete setup (do not connect to a wifi network yet)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Root the device:

<ul>
<li>Install KingRoot and JmzFireHDTool:

<ul>
<li><code>adb install KingRoot-4.1.0.249-release-nolog-201505211812_105001.apk</code></li>
<li><code>adb install JmzFireHDTool_v4.apk</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Temporarily disable otaverify via adb

<ul>
<li><code>adb shell pm block com.amazon.otaverifier</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Connect to wifi and open KingRoot on your tablet</li>
<li>Press &ldquo;try to root&rdquo;</li>
<li>Re-enable otaverifier

<ul>
<li><code>adb shell pm unblock com.amazon.otaverifier</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Open JMZ Fire Tools and press <code>Disable OTA's</code> and <code>Disable Ads</code> (most importantly <strong>do not</strong> install Google apps from JMZ)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Install a custom recovery:

<ul>
<li>Install TWRP Manager

<ul>
<li><code>adb install com.jmz.soft.twrpmanager-7.5.1.3.apk</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Install TWRP:

<ul>
<li>Run TWRP Manager and give it superuser access when prompted. Say yes if it prompt to apply patch.</li>
<li>Tap top-left of screen for slide-out menu and select Install TWRP.</li>
<li>Confirm Device Name shows &ldquo;ariel&rdquo; and then tap Install Recovery. At warning screen, tap yes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Download the following to Fire&rsquo;s Download folder (or download to computer and copy to Download folder).

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/uc?id=0B5VDSXB6iXSmTEQ3cnljNzJhZk0&amp;export=download">4.5.4 update zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bil-t/fire-hd6-android/blob/master/UPDATE-SuperSU-v2.46.zip?raw=true">SuperSU update zip</a></li>
<li><a href="http://downloadandroidfiles.org/file.php/?File=/Gapps/KitKat/Android%204.4.X/pa_gapps-modular-pico-4.4.4-20150308-signed.zip">Pico GAPPS</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Update to 4.5.4

<ul>
<li>Turn off wifi.</li>
<li>Boot to TWRP:

<ul>
<li>Power off tablet.</li>
<li>Hold down power and volume-up buttons at same time until you see “Amazon,” then release.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Install the 4.5.4 update:

<ul>
<li>Tap Install</li>
<li>Navigate to Download folder and tap the zip (twrp_ready_update-kindle &hellip;) and swipe &ldquo;swipe to confirm flash.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tap Home and install the SuperSU update zip.</li>
<li>Tap Reboot system.</li>
<li>Boot to TWRP</li>
<li>Install the GAPPS zip</li>
<li>Wipe cache/dalvik and reboot system.</li>
<li>Open JMZ Fire Tools and check if <code>Disable OTA's</code> and <code>Disable Ads</code> should be re-enabled.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Now open Play Store and sign in. Everything should work now! (When prompted to update store and/or services. Say yes.)</li>
</ol>


<h2><br></h2>

<p>*references:<br/>
<a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/fire-hd/general/how-to-downgrade-to-4-5-3-root-device-t3139351">http://forum.xda-developers.com/fire-hd/general/how-to-downgrade-to-4-5-3-root-device-t3139351</a><br/>
<a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=61832754&amp;postcount=10">http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=61832754&amp;postcount=10</a><br/>
<a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/fire-hd/general/how-to-install-twrp-boot-recovery-2014-t3160431*">http://forum.xda-developers.com/fire-hd/general/how-to-install-twrp-boot-recovery-2014-t3160431*</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turn Your Laptop Into A Wireless Access Point]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/13/turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-13T19:13:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/13/turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A year ago, while participating to an off-site workshop, a colleague wanted to show a new mobile application prototype.</p>

<p>For this purpose he needed a phone to reach both the internet and a laptop hooked to the local network. <br/>
Since wireless connection was not available the demo was at risk.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The laptop was running windows, equipped with a wireless network card and connected via ethernet to a LAN that gave it internet access.<br/>
With that in mind, it occurred to me that making the wireless card act as an access point could be the answer.<br/>
Searching the web I was able to find out how to achieve this by using the Microsoft Virtual WiFi mini port adapter, available on both windows 7 and 8.</p>

<p>I recently re-used the same technique to watch movies served from my laptop using a raspberry pie with a usb wireless Lan adapter.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how to setup the Microsoft Virtual WiFi mini port adapter in simple steps.</p>

<p>First you need to run a command line with administrator privileges:</p>

<ol>
<li>Locate the &ldquo;Command prompt&rdquo; program (Click Start, click All Programs, and then click Accessories under windows 7 or in the Start Search box, type cmd under windows 8)</li>
<li>Right-click &ldquo;Command prompt&rdquo;, and then click Run as administrator.</li>
</ol>


<p>Then you need to setup a virtual wifi by running the following command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan set hostednetwork mode=allow ssid=your_wifi_name key=your_wifi_password keyUsage=persistent</code></p>

<p>Replace your_wifi_name by the name of your network and &lsquo;your_wifi_password&rsquo; by the password you want users to connect with.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/cmd-1.png"></p>

<p>Then type the following command to start the hosted network:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan start hostednetwork</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/cmd-2.png"></p>

<p>Now all is left to do is to enable the internet sharing for this you need to got to &lsquo;Control Panel\All Control Panel Items\Network and Sharing Center&rsquo; right click the newly created virtual wifi adapter, choose properties, click on the sharing tab, click the first check box and choose the appropriate networking connection:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/settings-1.png"><br/>
<img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/settings-2.png"></p>

<p>To check the status of your hosted network use the command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan show hostednetwork</code></p>

<p>It will tell you information like the used channel as well as the number of connected clients.</p>

<p>Finally to stop the hosted network use the command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan stop hostednetwork</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Custom Scrolling With Meteor]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/06/21/custom-scrolling-with-meteor/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-21T15:15:41+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/06/21/custom-scrolling-with-meteor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve recently tried using <a href="https://www.meteor.com/">Meteor</a> to build a web application.<br/>
I used <a href="https://github.com/iron-meteor/iron-router">Iron.Router</a> to configure the different routes of the web application. Everything worked fine out of the box until I started using links with fragment identifiers.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First thing I wanted to add was an animated scroll behavior when navigating between anchors on the same page.<br/>
I was able to achieve this by overriding the <code>scrollToHash-function</code>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (animated-scroll.js)</span> <a href='http://bilal.eltayara.net/downloads/code/2015-06-21-custom-scrolling-with-meteor/animated-scroll.js'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Router</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_scrollToHash</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">hash</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">section</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">hash</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">section</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">sectionTop</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">section</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">offset</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">top</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;html, body&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">animate</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="nx">scrollTop</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">sectionTop</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">},</span> <span class="s2">&quot;slow&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<p>Next I noticed that when scrolling in a page and then navigating to a new one, the scroll remained at its last position.<br/>
The user experience was not acceptable.  When navigating to a new page, the user expects to land on top of the page and not somewhere in the middle.</p>

<p>To fix this behavior I used the Iron.Router <a href="https://github.com/iron-meteor/iron-router/blob/devel/Guide.md#hooks">hooks</a>.
I added a global hook that scrolls to the top of the page after the routing.<br/>
This can be achieved by adding the following code:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (scroll-to-top.js)</span> <a href='http://bilal.eltayara.net/downloads/code/2015-06-21-custom-scrolling-with-meteor/scroll-to-top.js'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">IR_AfterHooks</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">scrollUp</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;body,html&#39;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">scrollTop</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">Router</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">onAfterAction</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">IR_AfterHooks</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scrollUp</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<p>With these two customizations I was able to have a nice scrolling user experience with my meteor application. <br/>
What about you, do you have interesting customization to share ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up Wordpress on a Vagrant box]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/30/setting-up-wordpress-on-a-vagrant-box/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-30T08:50:16+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/30/setting-up-wordpress-on-a-vagrant-box</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently wanted to try <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> and explore its features.
For this I chose to install it an all its dependencies in a Vagrant box.<br/>
I followed the official <a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/Installing_WordPress">install instructions</a> and automated everything in provisioning shell scripts.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-30-setting-up-wordpress-on-a-vagrant-box/vagrant+wordpress.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Running <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> requires a web server, php support and a <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> database.<br/>
I chose use <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</a> as the box operating system. As a web server I chose to use the <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache HTTP Server</a>.</p>

<p>My provisioning strategy consisted of two shell scripts.
The first script called provision_once.sh is run only upon the box creation, and has privileged user rights. The second script called provision_always.sh is ran each time the box starts with a non privileged user rights.<br/>
This is specified in the Vagrant configuration file as follows:</p>

<pre><code>config.vm.provision "shell", path: "vagrant/provision_once.sh"
config.vm.provision "shell", path: "vagrant/provision_always.sh", run: "always", privileged: "false"  
</code></pre>

<p>The first part of provision_once.sh script installs required dependencies listed above:</p>

<pre><code>apt-get -qq -y update
apt-get -qq -y install apache2
apt-get -qq -y install php5 
apt-get -qq -y install php5-mysq  
</code></pre>

<p>After installing the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server, I needed to configure it, and create the required <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> database.<br/>
To setup the root password for the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server in attended way, one can use debconf-set-selections as shown below. I chose to go with no password as I was setting this up just for test purposes. <br/>
But this would have been too simple, as I expected the unexpected happened. The installation of the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server didn&rsquo;t go as planned. The <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server was failing to start. The failure was only happening upon the box creation, doing manually the same steps was installing the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server correctly.<br/>
After several attempts the only workaround I found was to perform the installation twice in the provisioning script:</p>

<pre><code>for i in {1..2}  
do
    debconf-set-selections &lt;&lt;&lt; 'mysql-server mysql-server/root_password password '  
    debconf-set-selections &lt;&lt;&lt; 'mysql-server mysql-server/root_password_again password '  
    apt-get -qq -y install mysql-server  
done  
</code></pre>

<p>Creating the database is rather straight forward using the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> command-line tool:</p>

<pre><code>mysql -uroot -e "CREATE DATABASE $DBNAME"
mysql -uroot -e "GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON $DBNAME.* to '$DBUSER'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY '$DBPASSWD'"  
mysql -uroot -e "FLUSH PRIVILEGES"
</code></pre>

<p>Next I needed to automate the download and the configuration of the Wordpress instance.<br/>
The part shown below will download and expand the latest <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> version from the official site.  It&rsquo;ll also configure <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> to use the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> database created earlier and generate the required authentication salts.</p>

<pre><code>cd /vagrant
wget -q https://wordpress.org/latest.tar.gz
tar -xzvf latest.tar.gz 
rm -f latest.tar.gz
cd wordpress
cp wp-config-sample.php wp-config.php   
sed -i.bak -u "s/database_name_here/$DBNAME/g" wp-config.php
sed -i.bak -u "s/username_here/$DBUSER/g" wp-config.php
sed -i.bak -u "s/password_here/$DBPASSWD/g" wp-config.php   
for i in {1..8}
do
    NEW_UUID=$(cat /dev/urandom | tr -dc 'a-zA-Z0-9' | fold -w 64 | head -n 1)
    sed -i.bak -u "0,/put your unique phrase here/s//$NEW_UUID/" wp-config.php      
done
</code></pre>

<p>Finally I needed to point the <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache HTTP Server</a> to the <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> site, this can be achieved as follows:</p>

<pre><code>sed -i.bak -u 's,/var/www/html,/vagrant/wordpress,g' /etc/apache2/sites-available/000-default.conf

echo '&lt;Directory /vagrant/wordpress&gt;' &gt;&gt; /etc/apache2/apache2.conf
echo '  Options Indexes FollowSymLinks' &gt;&gt; /etc/apache2/apache2.conf
echo '  AllowOverride None' &gt;&gt; /etc/apache2/apache2.conf
echo '  Require all granted' &gt;&gt; /etc/apache2/apache2.conf
echo '&lt;/Directory&gt;' &gt;&gt; /etc/apache2/apache2.conf

service apache2 restart
</code></pre>

<p>The provision always script is simple, it just make sure that the <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> is up running upon the box start-up.</p>

<pre><code>if [[ ! "$(sudo service mysql status)" =~ "start/running" ]]
then
    sudo service mysql start
fi
</code></pre>

<p>Finally redirecting the port 80 to the host, makes the <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> instance accessible from the browser, and ready to use.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-30-setting-up-wordpress-on-a-vagrant-box/wordpress-install.png"></p>

<p>The complete configuration is available at my <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/wordpress-vagrant">wordpress-vagrant</a> GitHub repository.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vagrant Powered Perforce]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/20/vagrant-powered-perforce/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-20T19:48:11+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/20/vagrant-powered-perforce</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-20-vagrant-powered-perforce/vagrant+perforce.png"></p>

<p>After attending the <a href="https://open.hpi.de/courses/softwareanalytics2015/" title="Automated Visual Software Analytics">Automated Visual Software Analytics </a> online course I had an idea on computing some new metrics deduced from the VCS (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revision_control" title="VCS">Version Control System</a>).</p>

<p>Since I want to make use of these metrics at work, my implementation should be
able to work against a <a href="http://www.perforce.com/" title="Perforce.com">Perforce</a> server, the VCS we mainly use.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In order to have the appropriate development environment I needed a Linux virtual machine on which Perforce is installed, configured an running properly.
I had previously used <a href="blog/2015/05/01/an-octopress-slash-vagrant-experiment/" title="An Octopress/Vagrant Experiment">Vagrant</a> to sandbox a development environment, and at that moment I knew it was the beginning of a long-term addiction.</p>

<p>Fortunately for me, Perforce can be downloaded free for up to 20 users.<br/>
My goal was to configure a virtual machine via Vagrant and provision it by installing a perforce server, running it and make it accessible from the host machine.</p>

<p>Interested ? Here&rsquo;s how to do it.</p>

<h2>1. Port Forwarding: Configuration</h2>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (Vagrantfile)</span> <a href='http://bilal.eltayara.net/downloads/code/2015-05-20-vagrant-powered-perforce/Vagrantfile'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'><span class="vg">Vagrant</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">configure</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="il">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="vg">do</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">|</span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">box</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;ubuntu/trusty64&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">ssh</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">port</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">2223</span><span class="w">  </span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">ssh</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">forward_agent</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="vg">true</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">ssh</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">forward_x11</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="vg">true</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">network</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;forwarded_port&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">guest:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">1666</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">host:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">1666</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">network</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">:</span><span class="vg">forwarded_port</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">guest:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">22</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">host:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">2222</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">id:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;ssh&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">disabled:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="vg">true</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">network</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">:</span><span class="vg">forwarded_port</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">guest:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">22</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">host:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="il">2223</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">auto_correct:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="vg">true</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">provision</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;shell&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">path:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;vagrant/provision_once.sh&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="w">  </span><span class="vg">config</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">vm</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="vg">provision</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;shell&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">path:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;vagrant/provision_always.sh&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">run:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;always&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nl">privileged:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">&quot;false&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="vg">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Since I was already using a Vagrant virtual machine I had to pay attention to using a different set of ports.
The SSH port forwarding is bound, out of the box, to 2222. It was not clear in the documentation how to disable it. After several attempts and some googling I ended up by finding the right way to do it. For it to work you need to add the following two entries in the Vagrant file:</p>

<p><code>config.vm.network :forwarded_port, guest: 22, host: 2222, id: "ssh", disabled: true</code>  <br/>
<code>config.vm.network :forwarded_port, guest: 22, host: 2223, auto_correct: true</code></p>

<p>Perforce uses by default the port 1666, I chose to use the same port when forwarding it to the host.</p>

<h2>2. Provisioning: Installing and starting Perfoce</h2>

<p>Next I had to install perforce and run it. I was lucky enough to stumble upon an article that revealed to me the existence of a public Perforce FTP server.</p>

<p>Knowing that, I used a first provisioning shell script to download the perforce server binary (p4d) and its command line client (p4).</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (provision_once.sh)</span> <a href='http://bilal.eltayara.net/downloads/code/2015-05-20-vagrant-powered-perforce/provision_once.sh'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/bash -x</span>
</span><span class='line'>apt-get update
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> ! -d <span class="s2">&quot;/usr/local/p4root&quot;</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>  mkdir /usr/local/p4root
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">cd</span> /usr/local/bin/
</span><span class='line'>  wget -q ftp://ftp.perforce.com/perforce/r15.1/bin.linux26x86_64/p4d
</span><span class='line'>  wget -q ftp://ftp.perforce.com/perforce/r15.1/bin.linux26x86_64/p4
</span><span class='line'>  chmod +x p4d
</span><span class='line'>  chmod +x p4
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s1">&#39;P4PORT=tcp4:127.0.0.1:1666&#39;</span> &gt;&gt; /etc/environment
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">fi</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>A second provisioning script, executed with a non privileged user, starts the Perforce server and does a connection attempt.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (provision_always.sh)</span> <a href='http://bilal.eltayara.net/downloads/code/2015-05-20-vagrant-powered-perforce/provision_always.sh'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/bash -x</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">export </span><span class="nv">P4PORT</span><span class="o">=</span>tcp4:127.0.0.1:1666
</span><span class='line'>sudo p4d -r /usr/local/p4root <span class="p">&amp;</span>
</span><span class='line'>sleep 3
</span><span class='line'>p4 info
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This script is configured to run at each restart of the virtual machine to make sure that the Perforce server is always started.</p>

<h2>3. Accessing Perforce from host</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth to note that if the second provisioning script is ran with a privileged user
the connection from the host was failing. I took me some time to figure out that starting the perforce server with the non privileged user, is the solution. I didn&rsquo;t understand the reason behind it but I was glad it was working.<br/>
With that in place, the Perforce command line client running on the host machine was able to connect to the Perforce server running on the guest machine with no trouble.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-20-vagrant-powered-perforce/p4-client-host.png"></p>

<p>Want to try it ? Fork it from <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/vagrant-perforce-provisioning.git">vagrant-perforce-provisioning</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Invest In Metadata]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/14/invest-in-metadata/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-14T22:24:07+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/14/invest-in-metadata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I had a discussion with a colleague about an effort he was making to classify our enterprise wiki content. <br/>
His prime motivation was the difficulty to track what was published, who publishes what and where different information are located.
Thus he was investing in building a directory for the wiki, by providing categorized links to the pages of interest.<br/>
Seeing this, I couldn&rsquo;t agree less.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/directory.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, my problem was not with the need but rather with the approach.<br/>
I was as well facing the same problem when trying to look for information in our wiki and persuaded that there is room for improvement.<br/>
Publishing a classified directory of shortcuts was definitely not the right answer. For me, the simple proof resides in the problem statement itself: if we aren&rsquo;t able to track the information how will we be able to maintain an up to date directory? Any human-edited directory is obsolete by design.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/obsolete-book.jpg"></p>

<p>Looking back at the evolution of the search engines, one can see how things evolved from static directories to dynamic queries with real-time suggestions.
This also confirms that using static directories is not the right answer.
The problem we want to solve here is not new. I&rsquo;m pretty sure that by now everybody have faced it at least once.<br/>
I had faced it in the past with my e-mails and my photos. For instance, I wanted a quick way to find e-mails related to a certain subject and I needed to group photos by occasion.<br/>
My first attempt was always to classify the data. <br/>
Easy, for e-mails I used folders in my in-box and for photos it was folders on my drive or albums when using a hosting service.
Easy but not free, I had to invest some time to classify the initial stock. For emails automated rules are of great help, for photos it was rather manual (Disclaimer: being a programmer I had scripted the photos&#8217; classification).<br/>
When done, I was rather happy, my data was organized, now I can find what I&rsquo;m looking for easily.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/photos-directory-tree.jpg"></p>

<p>Alas, the success was ephemeral. Sometimes I needed to classify an e-mail in several categories. Some other times I needed to find the photos of one of my children for a certain month. My static classification failed me and it wasn&rsquo;t a surprise.
Fortunately for me things had evolved in my favor.
When Google launched their Gmail I was very happy to discover the labels as a replacement of folders. I can tag a mail with one or several labels. Labels can be used as search criteria. Labels were the real answer to my need that I had worked around it using folders. With labels I was able to enrich my e-mails with searchable metadata.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/gmail-labels.jpg"></p>

<p>In the digital photography world, two things happened. On one hand, devices evolved, and adding metadata to the photos became the norm (timestamp, gps coordinates, camera model &hellip;). On the other hand, besides taking into account the photo metadata, it become easy to find a photo management tool with a face recognition feature. Thus, it&rsquo;s possible now to look for photos by combining all these information.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/picasa-face.jpg"></p>

<p>Taking a step back and looking again at all the cited examples, I can say that it&rsquo;s all about metadata. It&rsquo;s about adding &ldquo;data about the data&rdquo; and making it available for your tools. By exploiting the metadata, tools can offer not only unlimited alternate views, but also slice and dice capabilities.   <br/>
Getting back to our internal wiki problem statement, if you ask me how to solve it, my answer would be to use &ldquo;Semantic Web&rdquo; techniques to enrich the content with metadata, and provide a search engine that can exploit these metadata.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/metadata.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jamiesrabbits/4248396588" title="Obsolete Book - 5/365 by Jamie, sur Flickr">Obsolete Book</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/loopzilla/139024246" title="iPhoto 6.0.2 munged my directory tree! by Gordon Joly, sur Flickr">iPhoto 6.0.2 munged my directory tree!</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/blake4tx/2840242241" title="Picasa Web Albums - Add Name Tags by blakeburris, sur Flickr">Picasa Web Albums - Add Name Tags</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/frederickmdrocks/6160077394" title="Inbox Triage With Gmail by David Bruce Jr., sur Flickr">Inbox Triage With Gmail</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/psychemedia/2857518684" title="ORO resource splash page meta data by Tony Hirst, sur Flickr">ORO resource splash page meta data</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Things Every Software Development Manager Should Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/13/3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-13T20:07:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/13/3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are three practices that I found to be of a great help in my day-to-day work as software development manager.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2>Inspection is your friend</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s crucial to know how your code source health is.
Complex code tend to have a high maintenance cost and makes entry cost higher for a newcomer. Failing to apply best practices and recommendations can result in various bugs. A poor test coverage makes future development very likely to introduce regressions.<br/>
Static and dynamic analysis are you best friends to give you accurate indicators about your code health. They also help you take appropriate actions to cure the spotted deficiencies.<br/>
If you don&rsquo;t have this yet in place, all it takes is these simple steps:<br/>
1. Start by setting up a continuous code analysis process for your source code<br/>
2. Define a quality profile and break the build whenever the quality gateway is violated<br/>
3. Every time an issue is fixed, adjust the quality gate accordingly</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/inspection.jpg"></p>

<h2>Better double-check</h2>

<p>Static and dynamic code analysis can help you track the source code health but when it comes to technical design they are rather limited.<br/>
When software development manager drifts away from the code because of other duties that require his attention, code review can be a good help.<br/>
By reviewing the changes regularly the software development manager can stay up to date with the design changes and can intervene at an early stage if needed.
How to do it? By a continuous automated code review generation process:<br/>
1. Automatically create a code review for each new change<br/>
2. Keep the pace, perform the review regularly</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/diff.jpg"></p>

<h2>Get your hands dirty</h2>

<p>Quite often the software development manager doesn&rsquo;t have room anymore for coding. Unfortunately this can make him unaware of the coding conditions, pain-points and other important factors. If the team fail to give him a comprehensive feedback this can result in negative outcomes. <br/>
My suggestion, make room to code. Besides giving you an accurate idea of the work conditions of your team, you&rsquo;ll enjoy performing what initially made you want this job.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/hack.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/dumindaxsb/2873528646" title="On Screen Magnification by Duminda Jayasena, sur Flickr">On Screen Magnification</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jblyberg/3942639156" title="My eyes are starting to hurt by John Blyberg, sur Flickr">My eyes are starting to hurt</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/adulau/5136853276" title="Chris Nickerson at hack.lu 2010 by Alexandre Dulaunoy, sur Flickr">Chris Nickerson at hack.lu 2010</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things You Can Try To Get Back Wasted Commute Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/05/5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T20:52:33+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/05/5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you get stuck in the traffic jam everyday while commuting to work?<br/>
Would you like to make use of this wasted time? Read on.<br/>
I usually spend a couple of hours commuting to/from work every day.<br/>
Sitting behind my steering wheel listening to the radio was not very rewarding.  <br/>
So I started exploring how I could better invest this lost time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>
From among the things I tried, these are the once that worked well.</p>

<h3>1. <a href="https://librivox.org/">LibriVox</a></h3>

<p>LibriVox brings you free recordings of books available in the public domain.
You can listen to free audio books from any connected device or even burn them onto a CD.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://librivox.org/images/librivox-logo.png"></p>

<h3>2.  Commercial audio books</h3>

<p>If the book you&rsquo;re interesting in is not in the public domain, you might find a commercial audio version. Either on CD or a downloadable one, there are a lot of offers out <a href="http://lmgtfy.com/?q=audio+books">there</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/audio-book.png"></p>

<h3>3. <a href="https://www.ted.com/">Ted Talks</a></h3>

<p>Listen to free talks on a large variety of subjects. Whatever your interest is, there&rsquo;s a chance you find interesting and inspiring talks on the subject.
Ted app let you download the talks for offline viewing.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/ted.png"></p>

<h3>4. Online courses</h3>

<p>If it happens that you&rsquo;re following an online course, you can make use of the commute time to listen to the courses videos. Most of the platforms let you download the videos for offline viewing. Efficiency of this approach will depend on how much you need your eyes on the screen to understand the content.
What worked for me was listening to the video while commuting, and then reading the slides once back home.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/moocs.jpg"></p>

<h3>5. Google Play Books Reader</h3>

<p>You can make use of the Text-to-speech for Google Play content to read e-books.
For this you need to activate the &ldquo;Read aloud&rdquo; option form the top menu.
It only works with EPUB files, and I recommend activating the &ldquo;High quality voice&rdquo; option for a better listening experience.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://bilal.eltayara.net/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/google-play-books.png"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/74109564@N08/8119732223">Audiobook_logo_small</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>,
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/93112746@N05/11059505474">So many MOOCs</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Octopress/Vagrant Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/01/an-octopress-slash-vagrant-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T22:52:06+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/01/an-octopress-slash-vagrant-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my spare time, I like to try and learn new software technologies.
For this I use my Windows laptop. The problem is that after several cycles of installing and removing stuff, the laptop become slow. Its performance keep degrading with time until I take some time to reset its installation and reconfigure things.</p>

<p>Recently, after struggling with ruby installation on Windows I decided to reconsider Linux. Since I needed windows for other reasons, I decided to try using virtualization. I started by using <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> to configure a Linux guest machine. While discussing this with a friend, he suggested trying <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I visited <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> website and it immediately got my attention for its simplicity. All you need is a configuration file, a small set of commands and the virtual machine is up an running.<br/>
Playing around with Vagrant tutorial lead me to the idea of creating a sandbox for each software development experiment or project I work on.</p>

<p>I decided to test the idea of this sandbox on my next project: this blog.<br/>
As many software developers I settled on using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>/<a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> for my blog.<br/>
For this purpose, I needed a Linux machine with the required tools installed and a synced copy of the blog source. After several iteration I got to a stage where I&rsquo;m able to edit the blog from any computer connected to the internet. <br/>
In three steps I&rsquo;m able to deploy a blog sandbox and start blogging:</p>

<ol>
<li>First, install required tools: <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a>, <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> and <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>.</li>
<li>Second, clone the blog repository,</li>
<li>Finally, start the sandbox by switching to its directory and running Vagrant up</li>
</ol>


<p>It took me some time to get to a simple and repeatable process.
I&rsquo;m glad of the results as I&rsquo;m using the sandbox to publish this post. This experiment showed me the real benefits from using <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> and I&rsquo;m pretty sure I&rsquo;ll be using it in future projects.</p>

<p>Although this post is not intended to be a tutorial on how to use <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> or <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, I&rsquo;m going to mention a couple of things I found interesting. I&rsquo;ll also write about some difficulties I encountered and how I solved them.</p>

<h3>What I liked most</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Easy X11 forwarding over SSH connections</strong> by adding <code>config.ssh.forward_x11 = true</code> to Vagranfile. With <a href="http://mobaxterm.mobatek.net/">MobaXterm</a> running on my Windows host I was able to display the guest.</li>
<li><strong>Easy port forwarding</strong> by adding <code>config.vm.network "forwarded_port", guest: 4000, host: 4000</code> all traffic network to the port 4000 on the host machine, was actually forwarded to the guest machine on the specified port.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://docs.vagrantup.com/v2/synced-folders/">Vagrant synced folder</a></strong> enables editing the files from both the guest and the host.</li>
</ul>


<h3>What took me some time to figure out</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Shell provisioner as <code>vagrant</code> user</strong> and not as root: using <code>privileged false</code> in Vagrantfile didn&rsquo;t work for me when setting local version of Ruby via rbenv. I finally settled on chaining a call to a script with the specified user <code>su -c "source /vagrant/vagrant/user-config.sh" vagrant</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Blog preview only accessible from guest</strong>, at first I thought it was a problem with port forwarding, but finally, after tedious searches on the internet, I found out that binding the server to 0.0.0.0 in Rakefile was the solution. <br/>
<code>server_host     = "0.0.0.0"   # server bind address for preview server</code><br/>
<code>rackupPid = Process.spawn("rackup --host #{server_host} --port #{server_port}")</code></p></li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;re interessted in trying, the complete configuration is available in the  <a href="https://github.com/bil-t/octopress-vagrant-setup">octopress-vagrant-setup</a> github repository.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
