<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tips | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/tips/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-19T20:53:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turn Your Laptop Into A Wireless Access Point]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/13/turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-13T19:13:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/07/13/turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A year ago, while participating to an off-site workshop, a colleague wanted to show a new mobile application prototype.</p>

<p>For this purpose he needed a phone to reach both the internet and a laptop hooked to the local network. <br/>
Since wireless connection was not available the demo was at risk.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The laptop was running windows, equipped with a wireless network card and connected via ethernet to a LAN that gave it internet access.<br/>
With that in mind, it occurred to me that making the wireless card act as an access point could be the answer.<br/>
Searching the web I was able to find out how to achieve this by using the Microsoft Virtual WiFi mini port adapter, available on both windows 7 and 8.</p>

<p>I recently re-used the same technique to watch movies served from my laptop using a raspberry pie with a usb wireless Lan adapter.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how to setup the Microsoft Virtual WiFi mini port adapter in simple steps.</p>

<p>First you need to run a command line with administrator privileges:</p>

<ol>
<li>Locate the &ldquo;Command prompt&rdquo; program (Click Start, click All Programs, and then click Accessories under windows 7 or in the Start Search box, type cmd under windows 8)</li>
<li>Right-click &ldquo;Command prompt&rdquo;, and then click Run as administrator.</li>
</ol>


<p>Then you need to setup a virtual wifi by running the following command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan set hostednetwork mode=allow ssid=your_wifi_name key=your_wifi_password keyUsage=persistent</code></p>

<p>Replace your_wifi_name by the name of your network and &lsquo;your_wifi_password&rsquo; by the password you want users to connect with.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/cmd-1.png"></p>

<p>Then type the following command to start the hosted network:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan start hostednetwork</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/cmd-2.png"></p>

<p>Now all is left to do is to enable the internet sharing for this you need to got to &lsquo;Control Panel\All Control Panel Items\Network and Sharing Center&rsquo; right click the newly created virtual wifi adapter, choose properties, click on the sharing tab, click the first check box and choose the appropriate networking connection:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/settings-1.png"><br/>
<img class="center" src="/images/2015-07-13-turn-your-laptop-into-a-wireless-access-point/settings-2.png"></p>

<p>To check the status of your hosted network use the command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan show hostednetwork</code></p>

<p>It will tell you information like the used channel as well as the number of connected clients.</p>

<p>Finally to stop the hosted network use the command:</p>

<p><code>netsh wlan stop hostednetwork</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
