<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: retrospective | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/retrospective/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-26T12:45:34+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile Retrospectives Using Trello]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-20T20:31:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a distributed agile team working from Paris and Beirut, remote retrospectives are part of our rituals.<br/>
To conduct these remote retrospectives, we have settled on using <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a>. <br/>
My colleague <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/">BOURGAU Philippe</a> has <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">blogged on what we tried</a> and how we ended up by opting for Trello.<br/>
Since then we have made some improvements on speeding up the meeting preparation, and I think it&rsquo;s time to share them.
<img class="center" src="/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/trello.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As you might know, retrospectives activities are recurrent, it&rsquo;s not unlikely to redo the same activity a couple of retrospectives later.<br/>
So it was natural for us to start creating boards to be used as templates for the activities. <br/>
These boards served as a starting point when setting up a session and were improved continuously. <br/>
So how is this used practically ?<br/>
<img class="center" src="/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/gald-sad-mad.png">
In our case, a facilitator is responsible of preparing and animating each session. <br/>
When preparing the session, instead of creating each activity board from scratch, the facilitator had now a catalog in which he could choose the activities. <br/>
All he had to do is to copy the board, give him a specific name and share it with the team. <br/>
Each board contains a short description of the activity, and a suitable setup to conduct it.<br/>
In reality the facilitator still created boards from scratch, but only when no template was available.<br/>
But now, instead of doing it only for his session, he took the time to first create a template and then copy it into his session. <br/>
This way he would have contributed to the enrichment of the catalog and facilitated the preparation of upcoming sessions. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve been doing this for quite some time and I think it&rsquo;s worth to share it with the agile community. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve learned a lot form others&#8217; experiments and it&rsquo;s time for us to contribute back with what we experimented.  <br/>
I&rsquo;ve started publishing some of the templates I made to the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">Agile Retrospectives</a> space, it&rsquo;s a public Trello team.
As I&rsquo;m writing this post, there are six published templates. I&rsquo;ll soon be asking other contributors on the team to share their work too, so stay tuned for more templates. <br/>
I hope you will find this useful for your retrospectives, and if you do use a template and have any improvement to make, don&rsquo;t hesitate to join the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">team</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
