<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: retrospective | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/retrospective/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-27T21:23:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 Things That Can Ruin Your Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/07/28/6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-28T20:14:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/07/28/6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuous improvement is one of the necessary pillars when it comes to Agile.<br/>
Failing to improve your process won&rsquo;t let you unlock its full potential nor reach the benefits promised by Agile.  <br/>
But whether you&rsquo;re practicing agile or not, I&rsquo;m bet that you do care about improving what your doing.  <br/>
Identifying things to improve can be done by conducting a retrospective session.<br/>
Retrospective is a special meeting that takes place at the end of an iteration or a project.<br/>
It is a dedicated moment where the team take time to inspect the work done and try to spot opportunities for improvement.<br/>
Planning and conducting retrospectives is not hard, but some pitfalls might prevent you from getting out the desired outcome. Read on to know what are the 6 things that could ruin your retrospectives.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Totally winging it</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/totally-winging-it.jpg">
As any other work session or meeting a retrospective should be structured and activities prepared.<br/>
A retrospective is usually composed from several activities that will help the team spot imrovement opportunities and deduce relevant actions.  <br/>
To achieve this goal the activities need to fit well together, the timing already figured out and sometime materials need to be prepared up-front, like posters, cards, etc.<br/>
Improvising your session will most probably lead to poor outcomes. <br/>
My advise: take the time, 15 to 20 minutes are enough to structure a retrospective.<br/>
Choose a theme and the sequence of the activities, take some time to refresh your memory on how they are conducted, specify the time you&rsquo;re going to allocate to each one. Share the agenda with the team at the start.</p>

<h1>Fighting Hunger</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/fighting-hunger.jpg">
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needs#Physiological_needs">Maslow&rsquo;s hierarchy of needs</a> tells us that food is one of the very basic human needs. <br/>
You need to remeber that whenever you find yourself in the obligation to plan a retrospective during lunchtime.<br/>
It&rsquo;s better to avoid such situation, participants will be only thinking on when the session will end so that they can get to eat. At worst if you can&rsquo;t avoid it, do order food for the team, competing against hunger is a lost battle. <br/>
As a general rule, it&rsquo;s a good idea to have some fruits or candies available for participants. This will help them to remain energized and contributes to the good working atmosphere. <br/>
Don&rsquo;t forget to schedule a short break in the middle of the session, let people get out of the room, fulfill their needs, grab a cup of cofee or a bottle of water.</p>

<h1>Lightning Speed Retrospective</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/lightning-speed-retrospective.jpg">
A typical retrospective will take between 1h30min and 2h to deliver good actionable items. It&rsquo;s simply the time needed to collect the data, analyze it and deduce improvement actions.<br/>
If the team is lacking time, the last thing to is to shorten the retrospective. Doing that will only lead to the opposite desired outcome, wasting time on an inefficient session. <br/>
When the team find itself unable to allocate the appropriate time to its retrospective, my advice is to exceptionally skip the occurrence, secure the next retrospective and make sure the team identify what need to be done to avoid hitting the same issue in the future.</p>

<h1>Skipping the Starter</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/skipping-the-starter.jpg">
It&rsquo;s a good practice to start any work session with an ice breaker. Why ? Studies have shown that when a  participant in a meeting doesn&rsquo;t speak during the first five minutes, he usually remain silent till the end of the session. <br/>
You don&rsquo;t want that to happen to your retrospective, on the contrary you want all the participants to speak up and share their concerns and ideas on improvement. <br/>
By skipping your check-in activity you are giving each participant the permission to remain silent for the rest of the session.
Spending 5 or 10 minutes in an ice break at the start of the retrospective is good investment to make that can only improve the outcomes.</p>

<h1>Skipping the Desert</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/skipping-the-desert.jpg">
Retrospecting is part of your process, so as the rest it can and need to be improved constantly.<br/>
The check-out activity is your opportunity to get feedback from the participants in order to improve the next occurrences.<br/>
Don&rsquo;t skip it, make sure you plan a &ldquo;Return on Time Invested&rdquo; or a &ldquo;Plus/Delta&rdquo; activity to get insights on what can be improved.</p>

<h1>All Talk and No Action</h1>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-07-28-6-things-that-can-ruin-your-retrospective/all-talk-and-no-action.jpg">
Your team is extremely busy and improvement actions are piling up in a todo list somewhere.<br/>
Clearly the teams not improving, and it will soon start loosing faith in retrospectives and see them rather as waste.<br/>
This pitfall can be avoided by simply adding the identified improvement actions to the team backlog and treat them as any other task in the backlog.  Apply to them the same prioritizing technique and plan them accordingly. <br/>
In the Scrum framework this technique is called &ldquo;Scrumming the Scrum&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Simple Way to Run a Solution Focused Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/06/18/a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-18T08:03:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/06/18/a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While attending to a <a href="https://management30.com/events/two-day-course/">2-day course on Management 3.0</a>, on of the new things I discovered was the &ldquo;solution focus&rdquo; approach to improving things. Googling on the matter I learned that this technique come from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solution_focused_brief_therapy">&ldquo;Solution focused brief therapy&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/problem-solution.jpg"></p>

<p>In a solution focused brief therapy (SFBT) the patient is asked to focus on solution-building rather than problem-solving. This can be achieved by exploring current resources and future hopes rather than present problems and past causes. <br/>
First thing that popped to my mind when discovering SFBT, is its similarity to an agile retrospective.<br/>
Retrospective main aim is to spot improvement opportunities and come up with actions to make things better in the future.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been conducting and participating to retrospectives for several years now, but unlike SFBT, we were often digging to identify the root-cause of problems and then trying to figure out solutions.<br/>
SFBT opened a new perspective for me. Finding the root-cause in a retrospective is putting the effort in looking into the past. Applying SFBT to a retrospective implied not putting the effort on analyzing what happened but rather putting it in finding an action that can lead to a better future.</p>

<p>How can you do that? Here&rsquo;s the simple recipe I used.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When conducting retrospective I like to follow the structure proposed in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w8w-dFrmovQ">&ldquo;Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great&rdquo;</a> by Esther Derby and Diana Larsen. I always structure my retrospective accordingly.</p>

<p>I start by a <strong><em>set the stage</em></strong> activity to break the ice, and a <strong><em>closing</em></strong> activity to share appreciations or get feedback. You can compare these to a starter and a desert in 3-courses menu.<br/>
The main course is where most of the work happen, and it goes like this.<br/>
It starts with an activity to <strong><em>gather data</em></strong> regarding the last iteration from the participants followed by an activity enabling <strong><em>insights generation</em></strong> leading the team to <strong><em>deciding what to do</em></strong>.</p>

<p>The <strong><em>generate insight</em></strong> activity is usually where the team look at the problem, brainstorm to identify the root. Classical activities that can be used are 5-whys analysis, fishbone, etc. It&rsquo;s then followed by an activity to identify the actions and <strong><em>decide what to do</em></strong> like SMART goals, Short subjects, etc.</p>

<p>In a <strong>solution focused</strong> retrospective both activities can be replaced by a single solution oriented activity conducted as follow:</p>

<p>Assuming that the team did a <strong><em>gather data</em></strong> activity and identified themes to work on, divide the participants in groups of 3 or 4, each group takes a theme to work on. In some cases it might possible for the group to work on all the themes.</p>

<p>Ask the group to consider the following two questions:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Regarding the chosen theme, on a scale from 1 to 10 where do you think we are today?</strong></li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/rating-scale.png"></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>What action cans be done in the next iteration accomplish a +1 improvement?</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Then ask the group to work 4 small iterations, each one of 6 minutes as follows:</p>

<p>Iteration 1 - <strong>On your own, self brain dumping / Silence / Post&#8217;it.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 2 - <strong>Together, Share.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 3 - <strong>Aggregate &amp; Consolidate.</strong></p>

<p>Iteration 4 - <strong>Finalize &amp; prepare a 1&#8217;30 pitch to share with the other groups.</strong></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-06-18-a-simple-way-to-run-a-solution-focused-retrospective/post-it.jpg"></p>

<p>I usually remind the groups to make us of the SMART goals approach when deciding on the actions for the next iteration.</p>

<p>This recipe worked well for me, I found a good way to make the team discover new ways of identifying improvements actions. It&rsquo;s also a good way to bring novelty to the retrospective and avoid falling into monotony.  I&rsquo;m I&rsquo;ll be making use form time to time of it in my future working sessions. If you like this activity or would like to propose changes, please do not hesitate to leave your highly welcome comment.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thesaleswhisperer/14188549988/" title="problems solutions entrepreneurship">problems solutions entrepreneurship</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jogibaer2/5459043426/" title="Post-It">Post-It</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile Retrospectives Using Trello]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-20T20:31:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a distributed agile team working from Paris and Beirut, remote retrospectives are part of our rituals.<br/>
To conduct these remote retrospectives, we have settled on using <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a>. <br/>
My colleague <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/">BOURGAU Philippe</a> has <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">blogged on what we tried</a> and how we ended up by opting for Trello.<br/>
Since then we have made some improvements on speeding up the meeting preparation, and I think it&rsquo;s time to share them.
<img class="center" src="/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/trello.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As you might know, retrospectives activities are recurrent, it&rsquo;s not unlikely to redo the same activity a couple of retrospectives later.<br/>
So it was natural for us to start creating boards to be used as templates for the activities. <br/>
These boards served as a starting point when setting up a session and were improved continuously. <br/>
So how is this used practically ?<br/>
<img class="center" src="/images/2015-09-20-agile-retrospectives-using-trello/gald-sad-mad.png">
In our case, a facilitator is responsible of preparing and animating each session. <br/>
When preparing the session, instead of creating each activity board from scratch, the facilitator had now a catalog in which he could choose the activities. <br/>
All he had to do is to copy the board, give him a specific name and share it with the team. <br/>
Each board contains a short description of the activity, and a suitable setup to conduct it.<br/>
In reality the facilitator still created boards from scratch, but only when no template was available.<br/>
But now, instead of doing it only for his session, he took the time to first create a template and then copy it into his session. <br/>
This way he would have contributed to the enrichment of the catalog and facilitated the preparation of upcoming sessions. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve been doing this for quite some time and I think it&rsquo;s worth to share it with the agile community. <br/>
We&rsquo;ve learned a lot form others&#8217; experiments and it&rsquo;s time for us to contribute back with what we experimented.  <br/>
I&rsquo;ve started publishing some of the templates I made to the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">Agile Retrospectives</a> space, it&rsquo;s a public Trello team.
As I&rsquo;m writing this post, there are six published templates. I&rsquo;ll soon be asking other contributors on the team to share their work too, so stay tuned for more templates. <br/>
I hope you will find this useful for your retrospectives, and if you do use a template and have any improvement to make, don&rsquo;t hesitate to join the <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">team</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
