<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal development | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/personal-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-15T13:55:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My takeaways from Barbara Oakley's 'Learning How to Learn']]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2018/05/27/my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-27T14:59:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2018/05/27/my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I came across the Coursera&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn">Learning How To Lean</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course">MOOC</a>
while checking the list of the <a href="https://www.onlinecoursereport.com/the-50-most-popular-moocs-of-all-time/">50 most popular Moocs of alltime</a>.
On that list, Oakley’s MOOC was at the number one position. I was a bit
surprised at first to see this kind of MOOC being the most popular, but after a
second thought my surprise vanished. After all, isn’t the audience attending
MOOCs supposed to be genuinely interested in learning? In some way that was a
confirmation.</p>

<p>Beside the fact that it caught my attention, the title intrigued me. For the
past years, I’ve never stopped learning new things every day, and my interest in
learning has only grown more with time. I believe life to be a journey full of
an infinite amount of learning, and the challenge reside in learning the right
thing, in the right way. The MOOC seemed to unlock the secret on becoming an
effective learner, and that was more than enough for me to enroll.</p>

<p><a href="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/learn.jpg"><img class="center" src="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/learn.jpg"></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I found the course simple and concise, rather practical with the right amount of
theory to back up the concepts. It explains in a simple way the process of
learning and provides the attendee with techniques and tips in order to apply
the learning. Moreover the way the course is designed make use of the techniques
explained and demonstrate them. Beside making the learning more effective, this
provide the attendees with applied examples of the techniques.</p>

<p>In this post I won&rsquo;t be covering all the course, neither summarizing it. I&rsquo;ll be
just listing my main takeaways hoping it&rsquo;ll be also useful to you to. Regarding
the course itself, I do recommend it to all learners in any domain and any age.I
believe that the techniques and explanation can help anyone in learning more
effectively and easily any topic he&rsquo;s interested in.</p>

<p>In the course you’ll learn about the difference between focused and diffused
modes. When learning a new topic, one usually spends time focusing on the
topic,this is what is known as the focused mode. All learners will recognize
this mode as it’s the common way for learning. On the contrary the diffused mode
is when you let your mind wander not focusing on a specific topic, but rather
giving your brain the space and time to revisit and reinforce what you learned
when in the focused mode. Combination of both focused and diffused modes is
essential for an effective learning.The course introduces the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">Pomodoro technique</a> as a tool to
alternate efficiently between focused mode and short breaks. More importantly,it
invites the learner to look at the learning as a <strong>process</strong> and not as a
product. The product being the goal to learn something, and the process being
how you learn it. When one focuses on the product the goal can quickly become
difficult to achieve. The advised technique is to put in place a process of
cadenced learning sessions, that will help the learner achieve the goal, and
avoid procrastination. By splitting the learning in small chunks, interleaved
with short and long breaks, the learning become effective and achievable. This
approach will also enable the learner to alternate between focused and diffused
modes. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_learning_method#Deliberate_practice">Deliberate practice</a>,where
the learner practices everyday for 15 to 20 minutes a certain topic, is an
example of applying this technique.</p>

<p><a href="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/pomodoro-technique.jpg"><img class="center" src="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/pomodoro-technique.jpg"></a></p>

<p>The course discusses the benefits of exercising a physical activity in improving
the learning. When exercising your body, your brain will be in diffused mode and
will work on reinforcing your learning or generating new ideas.Sleeping is also
an essential activity for learning, it helps the brain reinforce the learning.</p>

<p>When learning, one must pay attention not to fall into the illusion of
competency. Learning something by reading a book or watching a video is not
enough, to avoid the illusion of competency, one must evaluate his learning by
doing tests,asking himself question, that will require him to recall what he
learnt. By doing that, one can improve his learning effectiveness.</p>

<p>Another caveat is overlearning. Repetitive learning of the same thing will not
make a better expert, instead one should aim to deepen his knowledge and
increase the level of difficulty of the exercises, that would improve the
learning. Learning is not just about memorizing things, what makes it effective
is taking the time to understand the why and the how of things. Understanding is
a key ingredient for effective learning. One good way of test your understanding
is to explain what you learned to friends and colleagues. Explaining will not
just help you check your understanding it also a way to recall your learning and
thus makes it more durable.</p>

<p>Metaphors are also a good technique to learn and memorize things, if you enroll
to the course you’ll see a good example on how to use metaphors for effective
learning.</p>

<p><a href="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/quote-henry-ford.jpg"><img class="center" src="/images/2018-05-27-my-takeaways-from-barbara-oakleys-learning-how-to-learn/quote-henry-ford.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I really enjoyed going through the course, it was the opportunity for me to
learn how to formalize a learning approach and to understand the importance of
the <strong>process of learning</strong>. If you’re interested in learning more, you know
what to do next.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/uomocolmegafono/5351734021" title="Pomodoro technique">Pomodoro technique</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/153278281@N07/39570229314/" title="Learn">Learn</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/klbeasley/5032405706/" title="Anyone who stops learning is old">Anyone who stops learning is old</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
