<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-19T20:53:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beating The Meeting Run]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T20:00:46+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just one full week in my new job, that&rsquo;s what it took me  to experience a new kind of sport, the &ldquo;Meeting Run&rdquo;.<br/>
And as a good friend of mine would say, like everything there are always two sides. <br/>
In what I experienced I encountered a good one and a bad one (and no there&rsquo;s no <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0060196/">ugly</a> one, at least not yet).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/time.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>
The good side was that my <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.fitness&amp;hl=fr">Google Fit application</a> started congratulating me everyday for meeting my 1 hour walking goal, and sometimes I would even hit that by noon!</p>

<p>In 15 years in software development, it never happened to me during work days ! (yes I know you might argue that smartphones and activity tracking applications are rather recent, so you&rsquo;ll have to take my word for that).   <br/>
This is great news, I finally managed to exercise and work at the same time, there&rsquo;s a hope for me to loose the kilos I gained this summer!</p>

<p>And as you might suspect there&rsquo;s no free lunch so where&rsquo;s the catch? <br/>
Well here&rsquo;s the bad side ; since all meetings were adjacent, it was just impossible for me to arrive at time to any meeting.<br/>
And it really annoyed me, I always used to do my best to be at most on time if not a couple of minutes before. <br/>
But I admit when I was able to do this my calendar looked a little bit different than it is now.<br/>
The same pattern occurred the whole week, and I started getting calls from people waiting for me in the next meeting.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, this is the end, I said to myself sadly ; bye bye punctuality and welcome reality &hellip;<br/>
Fortunately a little voice in my head was whispering &ldquo;no, no, no&rdquo; and when I paid attention I heard it say &ldquo;&hellip; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory">broken window theory</a> &hellip; <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Professionalism/Diane_Vaughan_and_the_normalization_of_deviance">normalization of deviance</a> &hellip;&rdquo;. <br/>
And it just hit me, it was clear to me that I was slipping into these anti-patterns.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/broken-window.png"></p>

<p>Accepting being late to meeting is a clear illustration of &ldquo;Diane Vaughan&rsquo;s normalization of deviance&rdquo;.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Social normalization of deviance means that people within the organization become so much accustomed to a deviant behavior that they don&rsquo;t consider it as deviant, <br/>
despite the fact that they far exceed their own rules for the elementary safety&rdquo;. People grow more accustom to the deviant behavior the more it occurs. To people outside of the organization, <br/>
the activities seem deviant; however, people within the organization do not recognize the deviance because it is seem as a normal occurrence. <br/>
In hindsight, people within the organization realize that their seemingly normal behavior was deviant.</p></blockquote>

<p>And worse, it&rsquo;s the first broken window I&rsquo;m inviting to my work habits. What next, I&rsquo;ll start accepting code with less quality, shipping untested code to production, and end up considering compiler warnings as just normal messages! <br/>
NO, NO, NO, this is not an option. <br/>
But how to avoid that?  How to avoid adjacent meetings? One might be tempted by defining a process to manage his calendar.  <br/>
And start thinking about rules, like meetings should not be adjacent, or they should never be scheduled to start at hh:00 but rather hh:05.<br/>
But how to enforce that, you might think about developing an outlook extension for that &hellip; <br/>
That was really compelling for the software engineer in me, but for the pragmatic developer it looked complex and too much, it also required everybody to be aligned with the rules when booking meetings.  <br/>
I needed something that I can achieve on my own, where I have full control to apply it, something that would be simple.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/punctuality.png"></p>

<p>Suddenly it all became clear. The solution is simple, do like the <a href="https://www.bitcoinmining.com/">Bitcoin miner</a>. A Bitcoin miner will keep a small fee for himself when validating a transaction.<br/>
All I have to do is the same, I&rsquo;ll just apply a tax to the meeting time and take 5 minutes for me.<br/>
This will let me leave the meeting 5 minutes early, of course I&rsquo;ll inform people at the start that I&rsquo;ll be leaving early.<br/>
And that&rsquo;s it ! A simple and actionable solution.  <br/>
Abiding by this rule I will hopefully get back punctuality and avoid annoying people by arriving late to meetings.</p>

<p><strong>So from now on, if you&rsquo;re in a meeting with me, be advised, there&rsquo;s a fee, I&rsquo;ll be leaving 5 minutes early!  </strong></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/4961717384/" title="time">time</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/26008085@N07/2739411797/" title="Broken Windows Theory In Action">Broken Windows Theory In Action</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/artistick-nik/5616580252/" title="punctuality">punctuality</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Invest In Metadata]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/14/invest-in-metadata/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-14T22:24:07+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/14/invest-in-metadata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I had a discussion with a colleague about an effort he was making to classify our enterprise wiki content. <br/>
His prime motivation was the difficulty to track what was published, who publishes what and where different information are located.
Thus he was investing in building a directory for the wiki, by providing categorized links to the pages of interest.<br/>
Seeing this, I couldn&rsquo;t agree less.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/directory.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, my problem was not with the need but rather with the approach.<br/>
I was as well facing the same problem when trying to look for information in our wiki and persuaded that there is room for improvement.<br/>
Publishing a classified directory of shortcuts was definitely not the right answer. For me, the simple proof resides in the problem statement itself: if we aren&rsquo;t able to track the information how will we be able to maintain an up to date directory? Any human-edited directory is obsolete by design.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/obsolete-book.jpg"></p>

<p>Looking back at the evolution of the search engines, one can see how things evolved from static directories to dynamic queries with real-time suggestions.
This also confirms that using static directories is not the right answer.
The problem we want to solve here is not new. I&rsquo;m pretty sure that by now everybody have faced it at least once.<br/>
I had faced it in the past with my e-mails and my photos. For instance, I wanted a quick way to find e-mails related to a certain subject and I needed to group photos by occasion.<br/>
My first attempt was always to classify the data. <br/>
Easy, for e-mails I used folders in my in-box and for photos it was folders on my drive or albums when using a hosting service.
Easy but not free, I had to invest some time to classify the initial stock. For emails automated rules are of great help, for photos it was rather manual (Disclaimer: being a programmer I had scripted the photos&#8217; classification).<br/>
When done, I was rather happy, my data was organized, now I can find what I&rsquo;m looking for easily.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/photos-directory-tree.jpg"></p>

<p>Alas, the success was ephemeral. Sometimes I needed to classify an e-mail in several categories. Some other times I needed to find the photos of one of my children for a certain month. My static classification failed me and it wasn&rsquo;t a surprise.
Fortunately for me things had evolved in my favor.
When Google launched their Gmail I was very happy to discover the labels as a replacement of folders. I can tag a mail with one or several labels. Labels can be used as search criteria. Labels were the real answer to my need that I had worked around it using folders. With labels I was able to enrich my e-mails with searchable metadata.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/gmail-labels.jpg"></p>

<p>In the digital photography world, two things happened. On one hand, devices evolved, and adding metadata to the photos became the norm (timestamp, gps coordinates, camera model &hellip;). On the other hand, besides taking into account the photo metadata, it become easy to find a photo management tool with a face recognition feature. Thus, it&rsquo;s possible now to look for photos by combining all these information.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/picasa-face.jpg"></p>

<p>Taking a step back and looking again at all the cited examples, I can say that it&rsquo;s all about metadata. It&rsquo;s about adding &ldquo;data about the data&rdquo; and making it available for your tools. By exploiting the metadata, tools can offer not only unlimited alternate views, but also slice and dice capabilities.   <br/>
Getting back to our internal wiki problem statement, if you ask me how to solve it, my answer would be to use &ldquo;Semantic Web&rdquo; techniques to enrich the content with metadata, and provide a search engine that can exploit these metadata.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-14-invest-in-metadata/metadata.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jamiesrabbits/4248396588" title="Obsolete Book - 5/365 by Jamie, sur Flickr">Obsolete Book</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/loopzilla/139024246" title="iPhoto 6.0.2 munged my directory tree! by Gordon Joly, sur Flickr">iPhoto 6.0.2 munged my directory tree!</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/blake4tx/2840242241" title="Picasa Web Albums - Add Name Tags by blakeburris, sur Flickr">Picasa Web Albums - Add Name Tags</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/frederickmdrocks/6160077394" title="Inbox Triage With Gmail by David Bruce Jr., sur Flickr">Inbox Triage With Gmail</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>,<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/psychemedia/2857518684" title="ORO resource splash page meta data by Tony Hirst, sur Flickr">ORO resource splash page meta data</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Things Every Software Development Manager Should Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/13/3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-13T20:07:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/13/3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are three practices that I found to be of a great help in my day-to-day work as software development manager.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2>Inspection is your friend</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s crucial to know how your code source health is.
Complex code tend to have a high maintenance cost and makes entry cost higher for a newcomer. Failing to apply best practices and recommendations can result in various bugs. A poor test coverage makes future development very likely to introduce regressions.<br/>
Static and dynamic analysis are you best friends to give you accurate indicators about your code health. They also help you take appropriate actions to cure the spotted deficiencies.<br/>
If you don&rsquo;t have this yet in place, all it takes is these simple steps:<br/>
1. Start by setting up a continuous code analysis process for your source code<br/>
2. Define a quality profile and break the build whenever the quality gateway is violated<br/>
3. Every time an issue is fixed, adjust the quality gate accordingly</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/inspection.jpg"></p>

<h2>Better double-check</h2>

<p>Static and dynamic code analysis can help you track the source code health but when it comes to technical design they are rather limited.<br/>
When software development manager drifts away from the code because of other duties that require his attention, code review can be a good help.<br/>
By reviewing the changes regularly the software development manager can stay up to date with the design changes and can intervene at an early stage if needed.
How to do it? By a continuous automated code review generation process:<br/>
1. Automatically create a code review for each new change<br/>
2. Keep the pace, perform the review regularly</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/diff.jpg"></p>

<h2>Get your hands dirty</h2>

<p>Quite often the software development manager doesn&rsquo;t have room anymore for coding. Unfortunately this can make him unaware of the coding conditions, pain-points and other important factors. If the team fail to give him a comprehensive feedback this can result in negative outcomes. <br/>
My suggestion, make room to code. Besides giving you an accurate idea of the work conditions of your team, you&rsquo;ll enjoy performing what initially made you want this job.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-13-3-things-every-software-development-manager-should-do/hack.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/dumindaxsb/2873528646" title="On Screen Magnification by Duminda Jayasena, sur Flickr">On Screen Magnification</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jblyberg/3942639156" title="My eyes are starting to hurt by John Blyberg, sur Flickr">My eyes are starting to hurt</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/adulau/5136853276" title="Chris Nickerson at hack.lu 2010 by Alexandre Dulaunoy, sur Flickr">Chris Nickerson at hack.lu 2010</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things You Can Try To Get Back Wasted Commute Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/05/5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T20:52:33+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/05/05/5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you get stuck in the traffic jam everyday while commuting to work?<br/>
Would you like to make use of this wasted time? Read on.<br/>
I usually spend a couple of hours commuting to/from work every day.<br/>
Sitting behind my steering wheel listening to the radio was not very rewarding.  <br/>
So I started exploring how I could better invest this lost time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>
From among the things I tried, these are the once that worked well.</p>

<h3>1. <a href="https://librivox.org/">LibriVox</a></h3>

<p>LibriVox brings you free recordings of books available in the public domain.
You can listen to free audio books from any connected device or even burn them onto a CD.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://librivox.org/images/librivox-logo.png">https://librivox.org/images/librivox-logo.png</a>&#8221;></p>

<h3>2.  Commercial audio books</h3>

<p>If the book you&rsquo;re interesting in is not in the public domain, you might find a commercial audio version. Either on CD or a downloadable one, there are a lot of offers out <a href="http://lmgtfy.com/?q=audio+books">there</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/audio-book.png"></p>

<h3>3. <a href="https://www.ted.com/">Ted Talks</a></h3>

<p>Listen to free talks on a large variety of subjects. Whatever your interest is, there&rsquo;s a chance you find interesting and inspiring talks on the subject.
Ted app let you download the talks for offline viewing.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/ted.png"></p>

<h3>4. Online courses</h3>

<p>If it happens that you&rsquo;re following an online course, you can make use of the commute time to listen to the courses videos. Most of the platforms let you download the videos for offline viewing. Efficiency of this approach will depend on how much you need your eyes on the screen to understand the content.
What worked for me was listening to the video while commuting, and then reading the slides once back home.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/moocs.jpg"></p>

<h3>5. Google Play Books Reader</h3>

<p>You can make use of the Text-to-speech for Google Play content to read e-books.
For this you need to activate the &ldquo;Read aloud&rdquo; option form the top menu.
It only works with EPUB files, and I recommend activating the &ldquo;High quality voice&rdquo; option for a better listening experience.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-05-05-5-things-you-can-try-to-get-back-wasted-commute-time/google-play-books.png"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/74109564@N08/8119732223">Audiobook_logo_small</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>,
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/93112746@N05/11059505474">So many MOOCs</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
