<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Bilal El Tayara]]></title>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-15T13:55:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[El Tayara Bilal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Started Sketchnoting!]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2018/07/15/how-i-started-sketchnoting/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-15T12:04:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2018/07/15/how-i-started-sketchnoting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Graphics are always something that catch my eye and make communicating ideas more compelling to my mind. Whether decorating a text or completely illustrating a concept with an image, I think it strengthens the impact of the underlying message. <br/>
One of my favorite demonstration of the increased impact drawing ideas can have is the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y1SDV8nxypE" title="RSA Animate: Dan Pink - Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us">RSA animation of Dan Pink’s Drive talk</a>. I’ve also seen the impact in brainstorming sessions when <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZgLbkbhvyUw" title="Graphic Facilitation (in a minute)">graphic facilitation</a> techniques are used by the group. <br/>
As well as I was convinced of the graphic facilitation power as a tool, I was also convinced, alas, that it’s not something I could do and get the benefits.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2018-07-15-how-i-started-sketchnoting/sketchnote-exercise-2.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My belief was founded on the assumption that it required strong drawing skills, talent ; things I don’t consider having. I was convinced to be right in my assumption and had accepted the idea that this kind of approach is not for me, without even trying. <br/>
Recently I stumbled on ads for graphic facilitation trainings. These trainings claimed to get people to start benefiting from graphic facilitation in two days. The first thing I said to myself is that it’s too good to be true.  <br/>
At best I’ll learn a methodology, and since I don’t know how to draw, I won’t be able to get the full benefits. Since my drawings will be awful, they won’t be of any good to me. <br/>
My belief started to change when a couple of friends I knew attended such training and showed me what they were able to do. I found that their work improved the way they shared their ideas. Even though they still had a lot to master the art of graphic facilitation, what they were able to achieve had a noticeable impact. Both told me that it’s possible for anyone to get in the starting blocks, start benefiting from the power of graphic facilitation with a reasonable effort.  <br/>
This positive feedback made me change my mind and start believing I had a chance. I was willing to give the graphic facilitation a try before deciding that I can’t do it. I just needed a plan now, and this is where chance played its role.</p>

<p>Lately at work, while I was discussing with a colleague at his desk, I noticed a book lying in a box. With his dark cover, high contrast text and drawings, the book caught attention. I looked closer at the title ; it read ‘<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sketchnote-Handbook-illustrated-visual-taking/dp/0321857895" title="The Sketchnote Handbook: the illustrated guide to visual note taking">the Sketchnote HANDBOOK</a>’. I was immediately intrigued and interested. “Are you reading this book?” I asked. My colleague answered me with a smile as I was cleaning the dust with my hand and reading its back-cover. “Well I’ll borrow it, if you need it, you know where to find it …”.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2018-07-15-how-i-started-sketchnoting/the-sketchnote-handbook.jpg"></p>

<p>The back-cover description was enough to convince me that I found my plan to start trying using graphics. The book is based on <a href="http://rohdesign.com/about/">Mike Rhode</a> personal experience. As a recognized subject matter expert, Mike promise to deliver a step by step process that will work even for people who think they can’t draw a thing! It looked like the book was waiting for me, and I had my plan now to get started on my graphic facilitation journey.  <br/>
I was so excited that started reading the book on the same evening. I found it easy to read and captivating. In two evenings I had finished the book and went through the practical exercises. The first half of the book explains the concepts and the step by step method elaborated by the author. The second half is rather practical and guides the reader to start applying the techniques explained.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2018-07-15-how-i-started-sketchnoting/sketchnote-exercise.jpg"></p>

<p>The best part is that the promise made in the back-cover is met, from the very first drawing exercise I realized that my belief was wrong, although I’m not an artist, I can draw ! Indeed, <strong>sketchnoting is about ideas and not about art</strong>, it&rsquo;s one of the key messages in the book. Moreover, beside explaining the process and the techniques, the book itself is designed as a collection of sketchnotes making it also a great reference to illustrate the explained techniques and a source of inspiration for the reader.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed reading this book and got the return on my time invested shortly, just after finishing the book I drew my first sketchnote for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SemHh0n19LA" title="Designing Your Life | Bill Burnett | TEDxStanford">Designing Your Life by Bill Burnett</a>, one of my favorite talks !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2018-07-15-how-i-started-sketchnoting/sketchnote-designing-your-life-bill-burnett.png"></p>

<p>If like me you’re interested in applying sketchnoting, and don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s something you can jump into on your own, I hope my post helped you change you mind. Happy sketchnoting!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Agile Autonomous Teams : A Paradox ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2017/02/25/managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-25T18:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2017/02/25/managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Agile teams are known to be autonomous and self-organizing.  <br/>
When I started fostering agility and encouraging autonomy and self-organization for the teams I work with, It was only normal to to face a situation where teams decided to do things their way, under the name of autonomy and self-organization. <br/>
The problem was that the direction they were heading in was not going to lead to the collective success of the enterprise.<br/>
My role was to help them succeed, thus I had the challenge of directing them while helping them improve their agility and thus their autonomy and self organization.<br/>
Is that an impossible equation to solve ?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you&rsquo;re new to agility you might think that this a proof that agility fails in an enterprise context and is only meant for a small team.<br/>
Fortunately it&rsquo;s not the case, agility, when well understood and applied, works at scale and delivers its promises.<br/>
Autonomy of agile teams is a must but it&rsquo;s not sufficient, along that, teams in an enterprise context need alignment.
Autonomy without alignment will only lead to anarchy, and this is something you don&rsquo;t want. Anarchy rarely leads to success.  <br/>
Only when both alignment and autonomy are present, agile teams can become successful.</p>

<p>This is greatly illustrated by <a href="http://blog.crisp.se/author/henrikkniberg">Henrik Kniberg</a> in the “<a href="http://blog.crisp.se/2014/03/27/henrikkniberg/spotify-engineering-culture-part-1">Spotify Engineering Culture</a>” and several of this talks.</p>

<p><a href="/images/2017-02-25-managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox/autonomy-alignment-kniberg.png"><img class="center" src="/images/2017-02-25-managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox/autonomy-alignment-kniberg.png"></a></p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Down here is low alignment and low autonomy. Micromanagement Culture, no high level purpose just shut up and follow orders.</li>
<li>Up here is high Alignment, but low autonomy. So leaders are good communicating what problems needs to be solved, but also they are telling people how to solve it.</li>
<li>High Alignment and High Autonomy means leaders focus on what problems to solve but let the teams figure out how to solve it</li>
<li>What about down here then? Low alignment and high autonomy. Means teams do whatever they want…</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>But how do teams get alignment ?</p>

<p>As alignment aim to make several teams work toward the same goals, it&rsquo;s by design an external factor to the teams.<br/>
Thus the teams can&rsquo;t achieve alignment on their own.<br/>
Agile managers are still an important piece of the puzzle, and fit naturally in the agile context.   <br/>
By helping teams getting alignment, they provide them with one of the necessary ingredients for their success.</p>

<p><a href="/images/2017-02-25-managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox/velib.jpg"><img class="center" src="/images/2017-02-25-managing-agile-autonomous-teams-a-paradox/velib.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I work in a fast-paced and constantly changing work environment, with geographically dispersed and culturally diverse teams, reaching alignment in such context is not an easy task. <br/>
As an agile manager I need to constantly drive alignment, in order to allow autonomy to build. It&rsquo;s about keeping the people and the work progressing in the correct direction toward to the goals, and it&rsquo;s not to be confused by staying &ldquo;on plan&rdquo;.<br/>
To accomplish this I practice consistently communicated, measurable, incremental goals.<br/>
In my next post I&rsquo;ll explain one of the tools I use to bring that guidance to the agile teams.</p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/44904381@N03/4424536847/" title="Vélib 2">Vélib 2</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/">(license)</a>,</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Software Development Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/04/30/building-a-software-development-team/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-30T22:06:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/04/30/building-a-software-development-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying to build an effective software development team ?
Here are some key elements that might help you.
<a href="/images/2016-04-30-building-a-software-development-team/Building_a_Software_Development_Team.png"><img class="center" src="/images/2016-04-30-building-a-software-development-team/Building_a_Software_Development_Team.png"></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Building a Software Development Team</p>

<blockquote><p>SCRUM</p>

<blockquote><p>Provide a SCRUM training for the team</p>

<p>Convince all team members take the lead in a round robin fashion on the scrum ceremonies facilitation (Sprint Review &amp; Planning, Retrospectives &hellip;)</p>

<p>Define the DoR : Definition of Ready</p>

<blockquote><p>Clear Acceptance test<br/>
Shared minimal design</p></blockquote>

<p>Define the DoD : Definition of Done</p>

<blockquote><p>Build pipeline is green<br/>
Minimal documentation</p></blockquote>

<p>Regular Backlog Grooming<br/>
Poker Estimation</p>

<blockquote><p>Story point as time unit is not allowed</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Ops</p>

<blockquote><p>Configure a continuous integration pipline</p>

<blockquote><p>Build (includes unit tests)<br/>
Code Inspection<br/>
Integration Tests<br/>
Performance Tests<br/>
Automate Tests</p></blockquote>

<p>Define Quality Gates</p>

<p>Build Pipline Monitor</p></blockquote>

<p>Code</p>

<blockquote><p>TDD / Test First</p>

<p>Clean Code</p>

<blockquote><p>Simple Design</p>

<blockquote><p>First make it work, then make it simple, only then make it fast<br/>
KISS<br/>
YAGNI<br/>
SOLID<br/>
Modular</p></blockquote>

<p>Understandable code</p>

<blockquote><p>Clear Naming<br/>
Comment Unclear Parts of Code<br/>
Self-documenting Code<br/>
Cohesive Methods and Classes</p></blockquote>

<p>Follow the Boy Scout Rule Leave your code better than you found it</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Team Work</p>

<blockquote><p>Define Work Agreements</p>

<p>Collective Code Ownership</p>

<blockquote><p>Define Team Coding Conventions</p></blockquote>

<p>Continuous Improvement Culture</p>

<blockquote><p>Improvement and exploration tasks are part of the sprint backlog</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is It Realistic To Manage Closely Several Agile Teams]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/01/26/is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-26T00:20:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2016/01/26/is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been recently promoted to manage a division in software development department of my company.<br/>
Till then I was used to managing one team at a once, not exceeding 10 people in size.<br/>
Now I find myself with 8 teams to manage having each a size ranging from 4 to 7 people.</p>

<p>In my previous role I was comfortable with adopting the SCRUM agile framework and quite used to play the role of the scrum master and to participate actively to the product owner role. <br/>
Some of the new teams were already trying to follow the agile practices, some were still working with rather a traditional waterfall approach.
So naturally I found myself driving the teams to adopt the SCRUM framework.
I made sure to share with them my return on experience and to point out the pitfalls and the small details that can make a difference.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/scrum.png"></p>

<p>Fortunately for me the resistance to change was less than expected. <br/>
All the teams were eager to try the new framework and to improve their agile practices.    <br/>
This is when things start to get a bit more complicated.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>Among the teams that had tried agile methods, some had tried the SCRUM framework before but ended up by letting it go. Some accommodated the framework with what they thought it would suit them better and thus were practicing a modified custom version.</p>

<p>This reminded me of the caveat entitled <a href="https://books.google.fr/books?id=pjLcBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT21&amp;lpg=PT21&amp;dq=%22Do+not+change+scrum%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ZLjZe7HpGC&amp;sig=fZakjNenlohycnYqsULErZxMPlY&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiVm-C3gMbKAhXLthoKHcC1AKgQ6AEIHzAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"><strong><em>Do not change scrum</em></strong> <em>in The Enterprise and Scrum (by Ken Schwaber)</em></a></p>

<p>Having observed that, it was clear to me that I had to bring the teams to the required level of understanding of the methodology and to help them in the adoption and ramp up phase.</p>

<p>Doing that was not a problem for me, on the contrary I enjoy playing the role of the scrum master in an agile development team. The problem was rather a capacity one, will I have enough time to do it right.</p>

<p>You might say, sure it won’t take that long to train a group of people to an agile methodology. <br/>
I can’t disagree with that, after all I had my scrum master certification after a two days training.<br/>
But what I also know, is that it took me nearly two years of practice to be able to take full advantage of the framework. So when I say doing it right, I mean working closely with each team trying to share with them what I learnt and helping them reaching the tipping point to becoming agile.</p>

<p>The couple of teams I had selected to start with showed high appreciation of the help they received and I could instantly see the difference and the positive impact on their day to day job.</p>

<p>But till now I haven’t managed to keep a regular pace to assist closely all the teams in this adoption process and this doesn’t make me feel satisfied. With all the responsibilities I have to assume I never get the time needed to accompany the teams in all of their agile ceremonies.<br/>
Since a couple of days I’ve been asking myself, assuming I had nothing else to do, is it possible to do such a close follow up? That’s when I decide to do the math.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/calculator.jpg"></p>

<p>For one team, per iteration of two weeks, I will need to allocate:    <br/>
- 3 hours for the demo/sprint planning   <br/>
- 2 hours to retrospect<br/>
- 2 hours to participate to the backlog grooming  <br/>
- 10 x 15 minutes of daily stand up</p>

<p>This leads us to 9 hours and 30 minutes per team every two weeks, multiplying this by 8 leads us to a total of 76 hours. So at the end doing the close follow up with all teams will require me to allocate 38 hours per week for this activity alone; a full time job!</p>

<p>Although this seem to fit in my working hours habit I doubt I will go that way.<br/>
Why? Because the expectations from my new role go beyond that, I have other duties to fulfill that are part of the role and that are time consuming too, nearly half of my time.</p>

<p>So what next? Well no doubt, I’ll need to make a choice, follow the most important things and delegate the rest.<br/>
First action is to ask a team member to play the role of the scrum master for a given iteration. All team members will play this role in a round robin fashion. <br/>
Second action is to skip attending the daily standups, this will let me gain back 10 hours per week, and I believe the teams will be able to conduct them efficiently on their own with the help of the assigned scrum master.</p>

<p>Next step will be to opt out from the retrospectives once the team is used to conducting them. Of course I will provide my notes to a team member and ask him to represent me. This will let me on the long term get back 8 hours.</p>

<p>So in total I will need to allocate 20 hours per week to perform the remaining activities which seem reasonable. I believe this close follow up will yield to a better results, I’ll be trying this and learning from the experience.</p>

<p>Interested in the outcome? Stay tuned.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2016-01-26-is-it-realistic-to-manage-closely-several-agile-teams/scrum-glasses.jpg"></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ansik/304526237/" title="calculator">calculator</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/neighborhoodnini/9650231200/" title="Perpetual Scrum Google Glasses">Perpetual Scrum Google Glasses</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/cadsonline/470108485/" title="scrum diagram">scrum diagram</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beating The Meeting Run]]></title>
    <link href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T20:00:46+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/10/19/beating-the-meeting-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just one full week in my new job, that&rsquo;s what it took me  to experience a new kind of sport, the &ldquo;Meeting Run&rdquo;.<br/>
And as a good friend of mine would say, like everything there are always two sides. <br/>
In what I experienced I encountered a good one and a bad one (and no there&rsquo;s no <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0060196/">ugly</a> one, at least not yet).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/time.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>
The good side was that my <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.fitness&amp;hl=fr">Google Fit application</a> started congratulating me everyday for meeting my 1 hour walking goal, and sometimes I would even hit that by noon!</p>

<p>In 15 years in software development, it never happened to me during work days ! (yes I know you might argue that smartphones and activity tracking applications are rather recent, so you&rsquo;ll have to take my word for that).   <br/>
This is great news, I finally managed to exercise and work at the same time, there&rsquo;s a hope for me to loose the kilos I gained this summer!</p>

<p>And as you might suspect there&rsquo;s no free lunch so where&rsquo;s the catch? <br/>
Well here&rsquo;s the bad side ; since all meetings were adjacent, it was just impossible for me to arrive at time to any meeting.<br/>
And it really annoyed me, I always used to do my best to be at most on time if not a couple of minutes before. <br/>
But I admit when I was able to do this my calendar looked a little bit different than it is now.<br/>
The same pattern occurred the whole week, and I started getting calls from people waiting for me in the next meeting.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, this is the end, I said to myself sadly ; bye bye punctuality and welcome reality &hellip;<br/>
Fortunately a little voice in my head was whispering &ldquo;no, no, no&rdquo; and when I paid attention I heard it say &ldquo;&hellip; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory">broken window theory</a> &hellip; <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Professionalism/Diane_Vaughan_and_the_normalization_of_deviance">normalization of deviance</a> &hellip;&rdquo;. <br/>
And it just hit me, it was clear to me that I was slipping into these anti-patterns.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/broken-window.png"></p>

<p>Accepting being late to meeting is a clear illustration of &ldquo;Diane Vaughan&rsquo;s normalization of deviance&rdquo;.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Social normalization of deviance means that people within the organization become so much accustomed to a deviant behavior that they don&rsquo;t consider it as deviant, <br/>
despite the fact that they far exceed their own rules for the elementary safety&rdquo;. People grow more accustom to the deviant behavior the more it occurs. To people outside of the organization, <br/>
the activities seem deviant; however, people within the organization do not recognize the deviance because it is seem as a normal occurrence. <br/>
In hindsight, people within the organization realize that their seemingly normal behavior was deviant.</p></blockquote>

<p>And worse, it&rsquo;s the first broken window I&rsquo;m inviting to my work habits. What next, I&rsquo;ll start accepting code with less quality, shipping untested code to production, and end up considering compiler warnings as just normal messages! <br/>
NO, NO, NO, this is not an option. <br/>
But how to avoid that?  How to avoid adjacent meetings? One might be tempted by defining a process to manage his calendar.  <br/>
And start thinking about rules, like meetings should not be adjacent, or they should never be scheduled to start at hh:00 but rather hh:05.<br/>
But how to enforce that, you might think about developing an outlook extension for that &hellip; <br/>
That was really compelling for the software engineer in me, but for the pragmatic developer it looked complex and too much, it also required everybody to be aligned with the rules when booking meetings.  <br/>
I needed something that I can achieve on my own, where I have full control to apply it, something that would be simple.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015-10-19-beating-the-meeting-run/punctuality.png"></p>

<p>Suddenly it all became clear. The solution is simple, do like the <a href="https://www.bitcoinmining.com/">Bitcoin miner</a>. A Bitcoin miner will keep a small fee for himself when validating a transaction.<br/>
All I have to do is the same, I&rsquo;ll just apply a tax to the meeting time and take 5 minutes for me.<br/>
This will let me leave the meeting 5 minutes early, of course I&rsquo;ll inform people at the start that I&rsquo;ll be leaving early.<br/>
And that&rsquo;s it ! A simple and actionable solution.  <br/>
Abiding by this rule I will hopefully get back punctuality and avoid annoying people by arriving late to meetings.</p>

<p><strong>So from now on, if you&rsquo;re in a meeting with me, be advised, there&rsquo;s a fee, I&rsquo;ll be leaving 5 minutes early!  </strong></p>

<h2><br></h2>

<p><em>photo credits:</em> <br/>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/4961717384/" title="time">time</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/26008085@N07/2739411797/" title="Broken Windows Theory In Action">Broken Windows Theory In Action</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">(license)</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/artistick-nik/5616580252/" title="punctuality">punctuality</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">(license)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
